<?xml version="1.0" encoding ="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Meadows</title>
    <description>A pleasant walk through computing</description>
    <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/feed</link>
    <link href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" />
    <item>
      <title>Posh-git Fork to Allow Visual Studio to Use TFVC and Ignore Git</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/posh-git_fork_to_allow_visual_studio_to_use_tfvc_and_ignore_git/images/git-plus-tfvc.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source Code: &lt;a href="https://github.com/bladewolf55/posh-git-tfvc"&gt;bladewolf55/posh-git-tfvc: A PowerShell environment for Git, modified to use with TFVC-based solutions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created this version of posh-git to handle a specific use case: a developer works for a company that requires using TFVC, but she wants to use Git locally to gain its rapid branching/merging abilities. Yet, she also wants to get the benefits of using Visual Studio's TFVC integration, namely CodeLens information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual Studio supports both TFVC and Git version controls, and you're allowed to choose which one to use via Options &amp;gt; Source Control. Except, not really. If your solution has a .git folder or .git file, VS assumes you're using Git even if you also have a $tf file or your solution/projecs are configured for TFVC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/posh-git_fork_to_allow_visual_studio_to_use_tfvc_and_ignore_git/images/ScreenCap_2019-09-24_20-46-29.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general solution is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename .git to _git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set environment variable GIT_DIR to the full path to the _git folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set environment variable GIT_WORK_TREE to the full path to the working folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add line to .gitignore to ignore the _git folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My modifications to the &lt;code&gt;GitUtils.ps1&lt;/code&gt; file accomplish that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, in the &lt;code&gt;test _git&lt;/code&gt; folder there's a file containing a Git alias to initialize a repo using a _git folder and the appropriate .gitignore and .tfignore changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not fancy, and I'm sure a better developer can improve on it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 20:04:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/posh-git_fork_to_allow_visual_studio_to_use_tfvc_and_ignore_git</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/posh-git_fork_to_allow_visual_studio_to_use_tfvc_and_ignore_git</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASP.NET Core Controllers - Exploring How To Test a Simple Feature</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/asp_net_core_controllers_-_exploring_how_to_test_a_simple_feature/images/header.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#setup"&gt;Setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#puzzle-1:-the-controller"&gt;Puzzle 1: The Controller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#puzzle-2:-the-service"&gt;Puzzle 2: The Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#functional-testing:-the-proof-of-the-pudding-is-in-the-tasting"&gt;Functional Testing: The Proof of the Pudding Is In the Tasting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#wrap-up"&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setup"&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a brief feature description: &lt;em&gt;When a user story is saved, if it's new then it's assigned the latest sequence number + 1&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How might this be developed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Test-Driven Development (TDD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...in a web application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...that calls a service?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="puzzle-1-the-controller"&gt;Puzzle 1: The Controller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, this article isn't specific to ASP.NET Core. But it's what I was working on at the time, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; I found the answer via a Core-specific article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate where we can have mental hiccups, let's start with the controller and work &lt;em&gt;backwards&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;    [HttpPost]
    public IActionResult SaveStory(UserStory model)
    {
        if (!ModelState.IsValid)
        {
            return View(model);
        }

        //Save
        //The service takes care of setting the Sequence property on new models.
        model = _storyService.SaveStory(model);

        return RedirectToAction(actionName: nameof(Index));
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is reasonable code. The controller passes the model to the service, and the service implements the business rule ofincrementing the Sequence property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a minute and ask yourself: What would your controller's unit test...test?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done? Now ask yourself: If I &lt;em&gt;hadn't written any code yet&lt;/em&gt;, what would I test for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe your first answer started off something like this in your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;
    [Fact]
    public void SaveStory_increments_UserStory_Sequence_by_one()
    {
        //arrange
        var service = MockUserStoryService();
        service.MaxSequence = 10;
        UserStory userStory = new UserStory(service) 
        {
            // set some fields
        };
        var controller = new HomeController();
        //act
        var result = controller.SaveStory(model);
        //assert
        result.Should().Be()...uh...um....
    }

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there's the trap. What I, and I'm sure others, find hard about unit testing and TDD is being clear on the dependencies of what's being testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In TDD, ask yourself, &amp;quot;What is this &lt;em&gt;unit&lt;/em&gt; going to do or change &lt;em&gt;by itself&lt;/em&gt;?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought would be, &amp;quot;Well, the Sequence is going to change. That's the feature, after all.&amp;quot; But that isn't what the controller is doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming no errors, the only thing the controller does is pass the model to the service's SaveStory method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service is a dependency, and we don't test a dependency's behavior. Let me call that one out, because it's crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In unit testing, don't test a &lt;em&gt;dependency's&lt;/em&gt; behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; control the dependency's state, and &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; return a value you've determined. What you test is what the unit is supposed to &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; with that value. This is why we mock dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, what's the unit test for the controller? I admit, I was puzzled until I read Steve Smith's article, &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/mvc/controllers/testing"&gt;Test controller logic in ASP.NET Core | Microsoft Docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should ensure that the service's &lt;code&gt;SaveStory&lt;/code&gt; method was called. I don't need to test &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; something was saved, only that it &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be. He's using Moq's &lt;code&gt;Validate&lt;/code&gt; feature for this. I can implement a similar feature in a self-created mock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;    // https://stackoverflow.com/a/11296961/1628707
    // This is one of those cases where it's simpler to inherit Collection&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;
    // and add a couple of needed methods.
    public class CalledMethods : Collection&amp;lt;CalledMethod&amp;gt;
    {

        public CalledMethod this[string name]
        {
            get { return this.SingleOrDefault(a =&amp;gt; a.Name == name); }
        }

        private CalledMethod AddAndReturn(string name)
        {
            
            if (this[name] == null) Add(new CalledMethod(name,0));
            return this[name];
        }

        /// &amp;lt;summary&amp;gt;
        /// Adds a &amp;lt;see cref=&amp;quot;CalledMethod&amp;quot;/&amp;gt; if necessary and increments its &amp;lt;see cref=&amp;quot;CalledMethod.Count&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
        /// &amp;lt;/summary&amp;gt;
        /// &amp;lt;param name=&amp;quot;name&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/param&amp;gt;
        public void Increment(string name)
        {
            var entry = this[name] ?? AddAndReturn(name);
            entry.Count++;
        }
    }
    
    public class CalledMethod
    {
        public string Name { get; set; }
        public int Count { get; set; }

        public CalledMethod() { }
        public CalledMethod(string name, int count = 0)
        {
            Name = name;
            Count = count;
        }
    }

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calling from the Mock class method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;    public UserStory SaveStory(UserStory story)
    {
        CalledMethods.Increment(System.Reflection.MethodBase.GetCurrentMethod().Name);
        CheckException();
        return UserStory;
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And using in the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;    // assume arrange and act before this, then
    _storyService.CalledMethods[&amp;quot;SaveStory&amp;quot;].Count.Should().Be(1);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id="puzzle-2-the-service"&gt;Puzzle 2: The Service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still haven't implemented the feature. In fact, arguably we shouldn't have written the controller or its test at all; the controller doesn't save the story, the service does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, let's write the test first this time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;[Fact]
public void SaveStory_sets_new_UserStory_Sequence_to_Max_plus_one()
{
    var service = new UserStoryService();
    var userStory = new UserStory()
    {
        //set needed fields. Sequence is null or 0.
        
    };
    userStory = service.SaveStory(userStory);
    
    userStory.Sequence.Should().Be(???);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. We run into a question of how to setup the Max Sequence. But writing the test is helping us. We need to answer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the service depend on something else to get the MaxSequence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If so, mock it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, &lt;em&gt;it will be a functional test&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's assume our service depends on a data service, and finish the unit test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;[Fact]
public void SaveStory_sets_new_UserStory_Sequence_to_Max_plus_one()
{
    var dataService = new MockDataService();
    dataService.MaxSequence = 15;    
    var service = new UserStoryService(dataService);
    var userStory = new UserStory()
    {
        //set needed fields. Sequence is null or 0.
        
    };
    userStory = service.SaveStory(userStory);
    
    userStory.Sequence.Should().Be(16);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For you to figure out: What if SaveStory were a void method?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="functional-testing-the-proof-of-the-pudding-is-in-the-tasting"&gt;Functional Testing: The Proof of the Pudding Is In the Tasting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, some piece of code is actually persisting data. There's no way to unit test that. If your service depends on an ORM such as Entity Framework (EF), then you can mock EF. But if you want to test that that your concrete UnitOfWork/Repository/DbContext/Whatever works as expected, you have to use a real database and check the values. Another example: if you at some point write to file, you'll need to write functional tests for that, and verify that what was written is what you expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonus: how might the functional tests look? Remember, these will be slower and likely run as part of a separate project, just like your integration tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp"&gt;public class DataServiceTests {
    Db _db = new Db();
    public DataServiceTests()
    {
        //In xUnit.Net, the constructor is used to reset the environment
        //to a known state.
        //There could be a lot of actions to take, so this is simplistic.
        _db.Reset();
    }

    [Fact]
    public void GetMaxSequence_returns_expected_value()
    {
        var service = new DataService(_db);
        //Our known starting point for MaxSequence is 10.
        service.GetMaxSequence().Should().Be(10);
    }
    
    [Fact]
    public void IncrementMaxSequence_sets_expected_value()
    {
        var service = new DataService(_db);
        // _db is reset before every test, so MaxSequence is 10 again.
        service.IncrementMaxSequence(1);
        service.GetMaxSequence().Should().Be(11);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrap-up"&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD isn't nearly so much what to do, as how to think. Especially, I find it forces thinking about how to decouple code and make it testable. The tricky part, requiring practice, is seeing what are dependencies and what aren't. Knowing what your unit is responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think learning from the simplest cases is great, because it teaches the principles to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 22:15:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/asp_net_core_controllers_-_exploring_how_to_test_a_simple_feature</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/asp_net_core_controllers_-_exploring_how_to_test_a_simple_feature</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remote Micro-Exclusions: Two Poor Daily Standup Practices</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/remote_micro-exclusions-_two_poor_daily_standup_practices/images/Symbolism-Leader-Group-Game-Figure-Exclusion-598036.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="remote-micro-exclusion"&gt;Remote (Micro) Exclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Remote exclusion&amp;quot; happens when remote developers are treated as less equal than on-site developers. This usually isn't intentional, but is instead a result of group dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some behaviors, such as not including remote workers in decisions because it's &amp;quot;too much of a bother&amp;quot; to contact them, are obvious when pointed out. But there are other actions that seem innocuous, yet contribute to the problem. These are&amp;quot;remote micro-exclusions&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the daily standup meeting where the bulk of the team is on site, and a few are remote. Here are two practices that can unconsciously devalue the remote team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="no-video"&gt;No Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three basic ways to communicate with the remote team in a live meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio Only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One-Way Video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two-Way Video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first two ways are a problem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio Only&lt;/strong&gt;: Unless someone on the remote team is vociferous, they'll be ghosts, rarely seen nor heard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One-Way Video&lt;/strong&gt;: To my mind, this is worse than audio-only. The implication is, &amp;quot;they can see us, be we don't need to see them.&amp;quot; The on-site team only see their avatars, at best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's critically missing without two-way video is the visual cues. How is the remote team reacting? What are they seeing at the main site? What is everyone communicating physically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-Way Video is a must because, &amp;quot;if words and body language disagree, one tends to believe the body language&amp;quot;&lt;a id="fnref:1" href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; And in those cases, body language can be 55% of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="remote-team-last"&gt;Remote Team Last&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the remote team always goes last, it's likely they'll always have less time. Unless a daily standup is being run really strictly, there's going to be conversation about whatever each developer is working on. If there's no two-way video it's worse. The &amp;quot;main&amp;quot; team will tend to dominate the conversation because they can see each other. Consider that for a team of eight, a fifteen minute standup gives each person two minutes. That's honestly plenty of time to report what happened yesterday, what's being worked on today, what's blocking, getting &lt;em&gt;quick&lt;/em&gt; answers, and setting up &lt;em&gt;follow ups&lt;/em&gt; on issues that take too long for the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is a standup management problem. &amp;quot;I'll email you to schedule a talk&amp;quot; should be said frequently. But the remote team is still devalued by going consistently last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="solutions"&gt;Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone must be visible on video. Work as if &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; is remote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Start&lt;/em&gt; standups with the remote team for a week or two, to remind everyone they're equally important. Then, randomize the order people go in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote work can benefit many companies and employees. It takes effort, but is a worthwhile practice to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://remote.co/qa-leading-remote-companies/what-elements-are-key-to-successful-working-relationships-with-remote-teams/"&gt;What are the keys to successful remote team relationships?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://open.buffer.com/remote-work-tools/"&gt;12 Essential Remote Work Tools We're Using at Buffer Every Day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.rightattitudes.com/2008/10/04/7-38-55-rule-personal-communication/"&gt;Albert Mehrabian’s 7-38-55 Rule of Personal Communication&lt;/a&gt; It should be noted that these oft-quoted ratios have their limitations and critics.&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 1 Aug 2019 20:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/remote_micro-exclusions-_two_poor_daily_standup_practices</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/remote_micro-exclusions-_two_poor_daily_standup_practices</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memstate: The Practical Argument for Big, In-Memory Data</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/memstate-_the_practical_argument_for_big_in-memory_data/images/header.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I listened to a fascinating episode of Jamie Taylor's &lt;a href="https://dotnetcore.show/"&gt;The .NET Core Podcast&lt;/a&gt;, featuring an &lt;a href="https://dotnetcore.show/episode-28-memstate-with-robert-friberg/"&gt;interview with developer Robert Friberg&lt;/a&gt;. Do listen to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friberg and his team have been working on &lt;a href="https://github.com/DevrexLabs/memstate"&gt;Memstate&lt;/a&gt;, an in-memory database. When I first started listening, I thought &amp;quot;this sounds like one of those interesting, technical edge-cases, but I'm not sure I see the point.&amp;quot; By the end, I not only understood, I wanted to start using it! But since I don't know how soon that will happen, here's the compelling meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relational databases solve a problem that doesn't exist anymore. That problem is limited memory relative to dataset size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your OLTP data can probably all fit in RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, simplistically, is how Memstate looks compared to a relational database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a relational database, the data is: Read into Memory &amp;gt; Changed in Memory &amp;gt; Saved to Transaction Log &amp;gt; Saved to Storage &amp;gt; (Potentially) Reread into Memory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/memstate-_the_practical_argument_for_big_in-memory_data/images/rdb-flow.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a memory image, the data is: &lt;em&gt;Already&lt;/em&gt; in Memory &amp;gt; Changed in Memory &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;Change&lt;/em&gt; is saved to Transaction log&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/memstate-_the_practical_argument_for_big_in-memory_data/images/memstate-flow.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of keeping all needed data in RAM has been around for awhile. Friberg recommends reading &lt;a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/MemoryImage.htmlhttps://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/MemoryImage.html"&gt;Martin Fowler's description&lt;/a&gt; of the pattern, and so do I. This tidbit helped me grasp how &lt;em&gt;common&lt;/em&gt; the concept is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key element to a memory image is using event sourcing.... A familiar example of a system that uses event sourcing is a version control system. Every change is captured as a commit, and you can rebuild the current state of the code base by replaying the commits into an empty directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is fantastically straightforward. Why persist &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; on every write? Why not just persist the &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt;, and keep the state in memory? In the past, the answer was &amp;quot;We can't fit all the data into memory, so you have to read it each time.&amp;quot; But as Friberg points out, you can configure an Azure virtual machine instance with 1 &lt;em&gt;terabyte&lt;/em&gt; of RAM!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friberg is clear that this method, like any, shouldn't be applied to all use cases. He nicely points out that even if you kept, for (his) example, all of IKEA's inventory levels for all its warehouses in memory, you &lt;em&gt;wouldn't&lt;/em&gt; keep all the product descriptions and images. Consider what we already do today with blob assets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don't (typically) store images in version control. We reference it externally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We keep images in cache because it's static.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And, of course, it also doesn't mean you &lt;em&gt;couldn't&lt;/em&gt; keep that data in memory.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine if your order entry system data was running fully in memory. Now, ask--not rhetorically--&lt;em&gt;could it?&lt;/em&gt; The answer will very likely be yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens if you need to perform maintenance? Surely it would take forever to replay &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; those millions of commands (transactions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friberg gives an example where a very large dataset could be loaded back into memory in about ten minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, while most of the podcast discussed big data, I wonder about small data. One of the persistence stores for Memstate is--you guessed it--a file. I think this would be a great solution for any app that needs a small database. The state would load fast, the app would run fast, and there wouldn't be any of the overhead of using a database engine.&lt;a id="fnref:1" href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to go a step further? If the store is a file, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; if the amount of data isn't huge, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; if absolutle top performance isn't necessary, then I'll bet the transaction information could be stored as plain text. And &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; means your data and history are future-proof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's how I like my data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://memstate.io/"&gt;MEMSTATE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/DevrexLabs/memstate"&gt;DevrexLabs/memstate: In-memory event-sourced ACID-transactional distributed object graph engine for .NET Standard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dotnetcore.show/episode-28-memstate-with-robert-friberg/"&gt;The .NET Core Podcast Episode 28 - memstate with Robert Friberg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/MemoryImage.html"&gt;MemoryImage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that, for instance, &lt;a href="https://sqlite.org/index.html"&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt; is big. I think it's just a .dll.&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 17:45:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/memstate-_the_practical_argument_for_big_in-memory_data</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/memstate-_the_practical_argument_for_big_in-memory_data</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grammar for Developers - Apostrophes: 3 Simple Rules, 3 Common Mistakes</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/grammar_for_developers_apostrophes_3_simple_rules_3_common_mistakes/images/grammar-for-developers-apostrophes.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a truism that (many) developers are not good writers. And it's not just style or composition, it's grammar. This has always puzzled me, since if a programmer makes a grammar mistake (using a backtick instead of an apostrophe, for instance), the program won't run. Maybe the problem is that they don't pay attention to the red squigglies in Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguably the worst error I see is wrongly using an apostrophe when &amp;quot;its&amp;quot; is possessive. Here's a  sentence to illustrate. Every apostrophe is correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Harvey's car's in the shop to have its radiator fixed before it's blown to bits.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expand the contractions and the differences between possessives and contractions are clear. &lt;code&gt;Harvey's car is in the shop to have its radiator fixed before it is blown to bits.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are three rules that, if followed, would take care of about 70% of the most grievous errors I see in blog posts, emails, business proposals, and technical documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I even made a fancy PDF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/grammar_for_developers_apostrophes_3_simple_rules_3_common_mistakes/Grammar%20for%20Developers%20-%20Apostrophes.pdf"&gt;Grammar for Developers - Apostrophes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="simple-rules"&gt;3 Simple Rules&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never make a pronoun possessive using an apostrophe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always make a noun possessive using an apostrophe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never use an apostrophe with a verb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="common-mistakes"&gt;3 Common Mistakes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right:  Unit testing has &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;its&lt;/span&gt; benefits.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Wrong:  Unit testing has &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;it's&lt;/span&gt; benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right:  &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;Carol's&lt;/span&gt; code is clean. Her &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;code's&lt;/span&gt; style is precise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Wrong:  &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;Carols&lt;/span&gt; code is clean. Her &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;codes&lt;/span&gt; style is precise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right:  He &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;runs&lt;/span&gt; that backup every day.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Wrong: He &lt;span style="background-color: yellow;"&gt;run's&lt;/span&gt; that backup every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="terms"&gt;Terms&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;noun&lt;/strong&gt; is a specific person, place, thing or idea:
Carol, France, house, radish, memory, Chipotle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;pronoun&lt;/strong&gt; is a generic, non-specific person or thing.
These are the common pronouns: it, he, she, her, them, they.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;verb&lt;/strong&gt; is an action taken by the subject.
He &lt;em&gt;codes&lt;/em&gt;. She &lt;em&gt;tests&lt;/em&gt;. They &lt;em&gt;demonstrate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 11:07:30 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/grammar_for_developers_apostrophes_3_simple_rules_3_common_mistakes</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/grammar_for_developers_apostrophes_3_simple_rules_3_common_mistakes</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Sugar: 'Accelerate', the Best Book About DevOps</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/devops/accelerate_notes_and_quotes/accelerate-header.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I run a Meetup called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Coffee-Quiet-Code/"&gt;Coffee. Quiet. Code.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I want to encourage developers to work together in the same casual space without having to discuss anything or even interact much. It could be seen as a far less rigid version of Mycroft Holmes' &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diogenes_Club"&gt;&amp;quot;Dionysus Club&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, a way to enjoy shared community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My inspiration came from people, often strangers, reading together in libraries, and also the sweet memories of my whole family reading their separate books they received as holiday gifts. In that spirit, here's a book recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Accelerate-Software-Performing-Technology-Organizations-ebook/dp/B07B9F83WM"&gt;Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps&lt;/a&gt; is exactly what it claims to be: high-quality, peer-reviewed research answering the practical question &amp;quot;What's really working in software development across all industries and team sizes?&amp;quot; There are plenty of opinions out there on DevOps. This book deals in facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote an extensive book summary for a client, which you'll find on my web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/devops/accelerate_notes_and_quotes/"&gt;'Accelerate' Book Notes And Quotes | Software Meadows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 14:02:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_accelerate__the_best_book_about_devops</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_accelerate__the_best_book_about_devops</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flatt's Posts/Casts Review #003 - Incentives, Emotions, Diversity, and Applying Bodyguard Training to Coding</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/20190616-1610 flatts_posts-casts_review_003/../images/reviews-logo.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019-05-23 to 2019-06-16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still in the discovery period for how to present my summaries of the articles and podcasts I read over a period of time. While I'm hoping the information is useful to others, it's primarily for me to A) continue learning, and B) look for essential patters in the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I'm going to present what I think are the top-level ideas across &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the material, and the top ideas for each episode. This should make the information easier to digest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, since I highlighted it in the title, here's the link and notes on the Bodyguard podcast and how I'd apply them to development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/podcast-513-be-your-own-bodyguard/"&gt;Art of Manliness #513 Be Your Own Bodyguard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These are self-defence principles, and apply to potentially dangerous situations. &lt;strong&gt;But note how they also apply to coding!&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoidance is the most important thing you can practice. (&lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deescalation is the next most important. (&lt;strong&gt;find/fix bugs fast&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where are your exits? (&lt;strong&gt;version control&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IF there's a fight, what are your three or four &amp;quot;go to techniques you practice all the time&amp;quot;? (&lt;strong&gt;logging, alerts, debugging&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regularly simulate and practice stress situations in class. (&lt;strong&gt;disaster testing&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn from people who've experienced it. (&lt;strong&gt;involve users&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the legal impact?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="essential-learnings"&gt;Essential Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align incentives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotions drive our decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study multiple subjects (generalize) and apply to your specialty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversity is highly beneficial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.leadingagile.com/podcast/what-is-a-well-formed-backlog/"&gt;Leading Agile - What is a Well-Formed Backlog? w/ Jeff Howey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating clear characteristics of a well-formed backlog is valuable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the criteria simple and short as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the terms and make sure everyone understands them. (Publish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Howey's characterstics: Clearly Prioritized, Linked to What's Important, Shared Understanding, Identify Dependencies, Clear Acceptance Criteria, Clear Definitions of &amp;quot;Done&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Ready&amp;quot;, Good Enough to Start a Conversation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/psychology-of-investing/"&gt;Art of Manliness #511: Mastering the Psychology of Investing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We think bad things happening are dramatically less likely than good things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The more complex and dynamic a system is, the more simple your solution needs to be.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;There's a weak correlation between knowing the right thing to do and actually doing it.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our decisions are strongly influenced by our bodies and emotions. Don't code upset!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humans are terrible at probability. They tend to reason in group terms, and conform to the group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/generalist-specialist-david-epstein-interview/"&gt;Art of Manliness #512: Why Generalists Triumph in a Specialized World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tiger Woods specialized. Roger Federer generalized until his twenties when he settled on tennis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;quot;ten thousand hours to become an expert&amp;quot; research examined specific fields that, it turns out, yield well to early specializing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the time kids are better off delaying specialization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generalists are better at new situations because they can synthesize and apply previous experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299506"&gt;Developer Tea - Mental Models w/Gabriel Weinberg Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299507"&gt;Developer Tea - Mental Models w/Gabriel Weinberg Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book of 300 mental models, i.e. &amp;quot;fancy word for concepts&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Models Weinberg thinks managers/developers often miss:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunity Costs: &amp;quot;The cost of what you're working on is what you're not working on.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing Function: &amp;quot;Scheduled process to force everyone to think critically.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find root cause using the Five Whys Model, asking &amp;quot;why?&amp;quot; until getting to the root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;I want to do this thing not because it's imporant, but because it's more important that all these other things.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299950"&gt;Developer Tea - 3 Assumptions That Can Hurt Your Job Search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you get turned down that means you are incapable of doing that job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone is going to read your whole resume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications to jobs are how people get jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Imagine you're trying to find a job without job boards being available. What else can you do to find a job?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299948"&gt;Developer Tea - Aligning Incentives w/ Lambda School CTO - Ben Nelson (part 1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299949"&gt;Developer Tea - Aligning Incentives w/ Lambda School CTO - Ben Nelson (part 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lambda School doesn't charge tuition for its education, and only makes money when its graduates get a job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very high bar for getting in. They're looking for grit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incentive Alignment. Both sides are working toward the same goal, and only succeed if the goal is achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hanselminutes.com/687/how-to-build-an-inclusive-conference-with-saron-yitbarek"&gt;Hanselminutes: How to build an inclusive conference with Saron Yitbarek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://codelandconf.com/"&gt;Codeland Conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yitbarek's goal in the conference is to celebrate coding, not the tools, and to be the most inclusive conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She mentions a study of people who do/don't finish computer science degrees. Those who do have a higher threshold for confusion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gimletmedia.com/shows/science-vs/awhklj"&gt;Science Vs. - How Bad Science Killed A President&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garfield died two and a half months after being shot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Among those who tried to help were Alexander Graham Bell with a new invention: a metal detector!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite Joseph Lister lecturing about bacteria and how to kill them for five years, doctors still don't believe it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So, basically, the doctors are digging around in Garfield's body with grubby hands, causing infection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nine years later, partly due to Garfield's death, doctors believe in germs and are sterilizing everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.growthmindsetpodcast.com/blog/2019/scott-brinker"&gt;Growth Mindset #59 - The World of Martech - Scott Brinker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One interesting comment was that Brinker thought marketers had an easier time experimenting--such as using A-B testing--that developers. (He was talking about the idea of Agile Marketing.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/300682"&gt;Developer Tea - Test Driven Meetings - Measuring Outputs and Side Effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at a meeting as if it's made up of methods. A one-on-one meeting might have a &amp;quot;feedback function,&amp;quot; which is a unit test idea. So look at the inputs and outputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But we also want to look at meetings as integration tests. What are the side effects, both positive and negative?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here's what Jonathan suggests in trying to apply the idea
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before the meeting, write down the outputs and the side effects that you desire from the meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Announce the outcome(s) and side effect(s) at the top of meeting so everyone is oriented toward them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/aristotle-living-the-good-life/"&gt;Art of Manliness #515 - Aristotle's Wisdom on Living the Good Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://edithhall.co.uk/"&gt;Edith Hall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0735220808/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0735220808&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=stucosuccess&amp;amp;linkId=FSXA3GZUT5SFDAZ4"&gt;Aristotle’s Way: How Ancient Wisdom Can Change Your Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aristotle wanted people to find their telos (purpose). Hall thinks today's education reduces the variety of exposure kids get to things like the arts, reducing their ability to find their telos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/300990"&gt;Developer Tea - How Can Two Rational People Disagree?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the same data, the frame parameters are different.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: Choosing between a bug or feature. Developer says feature because his frame is long-term. Manager says bug because his frame is short-term. Both are rationally good choices given the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often, in conflict, desires and incentives are the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.growthmindsetpodcast.com/blog/2019/niall-mccann"&gt;Growth Mindset - Doing the Difficult Thing - Dr Niall McCann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspiring and humbling. The guy's amazing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out what motivates those who can help you attain your goal, AND&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align their incentives to yours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do what you're doing first because you enjoy it. But also show how success has layers of benefits. Example: McCann's organization protecting a swathe of land not only prevented mass killing of elephants, but also raised local employment, the success increased donorship, and tourism increased because the animals were there to be seen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're not really a conservationist unless you've &lt;em&gt;conserved&lt;/em&gt; something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/podcast-516-how-to-lead-an-unstoppable-team/"&gt;Art of Manliness #516 - How to Lead an Unstoppable Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://alden-mills.com/"&gt;Alden Mills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0062876155/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0062876155&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=stucosuccess&amp;amp;linkId=FSXA3GZUT5SFDAZ4"&gt;Unstoppable Teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mills is fantastically clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to lead yourself first before you can lead others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a team means building relationships, which involves feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CARE Loop
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect&lt;/strong&gt; The real goal in connecting is to build trust.&lt;br /&gt;
Three tools: communication, commitment, credibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Achieve&lt;/strong&gt; Set direction.&lt;br /&gt;
Five A's: Aspiring (which he's using like &amp;quot;inspiring&amp;quot;), Assume they can do the job, Assess what they're doing, Appreciate their efforts internally and externally, and ????&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respect&lt;/strong&gt; Goal of respect is contribution, and requires mutual respect. To get everyone contributing their ideas, skills, etc.&lt;br /&gt;
Want people to be willing to say &amp;quot;I made a mistake,&amp;quot; then answer three questions: what happened, what I was trying to achieve, what I'm going to do about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empower&lt;/strong&gt; Getting people to think like owners.&lt;br /&gt;
Three Es: Educating, Enabling, Engaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gimletmedia.com/shows/science-vs/brh824"&gt;Sciene Vs. - SHARKS!!!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top speed of Great Whites, in just a couple of tail flicks, from 1mph to 25mph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sharks &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; smell blood in an Olympic-size swimming pool. They smell as well as other fish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From 2010-2012, more people died from TVs tipping over onto them (51) than from shark attacks (3). 124 shark bites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no such thing as a rogue shark (like &lt;em&gt;Jaws&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One quarter of shark species are threatened with extinction...including the Great White.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dotnetcore.show/episode-27-blazroed-with-chris-sainty/"&gt;.NET Core Podcast #27 - Blazored with Chris Sainty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chrissainty.com/"&gt;Chris Sainty - Building with Blazor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Blazored"&gt;Blazored&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What's so great about Blazor?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to write truly full stack applications using just C#&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opens up using NuGet instead of waiting for a new javascript framework's ecosystem to build up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On security of running a C# dll in the browser, Chris points out WebAssembly runs in the same sandbox as javascript. So, no more or less secure than javascript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But, it's still in early development. Not ready for general production use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we take on a dependency into our applications, if you're taking on someone else's code, you're always taking on a level of risk, and it's up to you to assess that level and go from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 16:13:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/20190616-1610 flatts_posts-casts_review_003</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/20190616-1610 flatts_posts-casts_review_003</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Sugar: Applying Kanban Principles to Your Personal Task List</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_applying_kanban_principles_to_your_personal_task_list/images/vertical-task-list.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us use Kanban boards (or you might be calling them Scrum boards) on work projects. And, we might use &lt;a href="https://trello.com/"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; for some home projects. But most people probably &lt;em&gt;aren't&lt;/em&gt; using them for their daily task lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of To Do apps out there, but here's a &amp;quot;first principles&amp;quot; approach using two lists. I do this in &lt;a href="http://keep.google.com"&gt;Google Keep&lt;/a&gt;, but it could as easily be done on paper, which is the inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;TODAY
- [ ] Finish base page
- [ ] Start home controllers
- [ ] Buy diapers at lunch

WAITING ON
- [ ] Time approval from Florence (emailed 5/12 3p)

SOON (limit 5)
- [ ] Read *Accelerate*
- [ ] Prepare for DevOps conference
- [ ] Call Marcus about tennis Thu
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;PERSONAL BACKLOG
- [ ] Plan Vinit's birthday
- [ ] Add user stories to MyCoolProject  
etc.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Keep, or a text file, it's easy to move tasks around. On paper, you might write in pencil and renumber priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, this is the same as a Kanban flow, just rotated 90 degrees. It's easy to update and change, which is critical to capturing thoughts quickly so they don't get lost. The software (or hardware) gets out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 11:34:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_applying_kanban_principles_to_your_personal_task_list</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_applying_kanban_principles_to_your_personal_task_list</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joe Developer: When (not) to Drink Coffee</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee/images/coffee-clock.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-06-10 15:03:00 This is an update of an article I wrote a few years ago.&lt;br /&gt;
2019-06-11 09:25:38 Significant update to call out when to drink coffee and other health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-gist"&gt;The Gist&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should drink coffee between 9:30 and 11:30, and &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; also between 1:30 and 5:00.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drinking 4-5 8oz cups per day has other health benefits. Quoted:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of cancer up to 20 percent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of heart disease by 5 percent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of Type 2 diabetes by 30 percent; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of Parkinson's disease by 30 percent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unless you're pregnant. If pregnant, coffee can slightly increase the risk of miscarriage.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science shows drinking coffee first thing in the morning negatively affects one’s circadian rhythm by inhibiting the production of cortisol, which the body uses to naturally wake us up. Drinking coffee when cortisol levels are falling helps us stay evenly alert. The recommended times are based on the average person who gets up around 6:30am. Adjust accordingly for your own consistent wake time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best summary for both time-of-day and health benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/geoffrey-james/scientists-just-discovered-best-time-of-day-to-drink-your-first-cup-of-coffee.html"&gt;The Best Time of Day to Drink Coffee, According to Science | Inc.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most entertaining summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.ilovecoffee.jp/posts/view/57"&gt;The best time to drink coffee according to science - I Love Coffee&lt;/a&gt; (with infographics!!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last entry seems to have begat many others. It’s my favorite. It makes me happy to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee/images/2019-06-11_09-38-22.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these articles discusses &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to shift your coffee consumption, which is a shame. It's like telling a smoker, &amp;quot;just quit.&amp;quot; The thing is, cortisol production doesn't just leap back into action. I've taken &lt;a href="https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-22008/budesonide-oral/details"&gt;budesonide&lt;/a&gt;, which decreases cortisol production, and the weaning off period is 2-4 weeks. So, I recommend making the change gradually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-article-trail"&gt;The Article Trail&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first read &lt;a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3034375/coffee-week/the-new-habit-challenge-drink-your-coffee-when-science-tells-you-to"&gt;this 2014 article&lt;/a&gt; about why you shouldn’t drink coffee first thing in the morning, i.e. right after getting up. Curious, I tried to find out more on the subject. I turned out there are several similar articles. In all cases, the stories originate from an article by Steven Miller, Ph.D., &lt;a href="http://neurosciencedc.blogspot.jp/2013/10/the-best-time-for-your-coffee.html"&gt;The Best Time for Your Coffee&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Dr Miller is a scientist, and he cites his sources, and he’s clear about what he’s saying and not saying. Check out the comments on his article; he defends against a few hostile readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where did he get his data? That’s from a study in 2009, the sciency-named &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2684472/"&gt;Modified-Release Hydrocortisone to Provide Circadian Cortisol Profiles&lt;/a&gt;. This article, which has 80% words I don’t understand, includes this graphic showing natural peak cortisol levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee/images/ScreenCap_2019-06-10_15-21-37.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="whats-what"&gt;What’s What?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Miller doesn’t point to a specific study proving that people should drink coffee at a particular time. He states his opinion based on the research. I liked his interesting pharmacological approach (emphases are mine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drug tolerance is an important subject, especially in the case of caffeine since &lt;em&gt;most of us overuse this drug&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, if we are drinking caffeine at a time when your cortisol concentration in the blood is at its peak, you probably should not be drinking it. This is because cortisol production is strongly related to your level of alertness and it just so happens that cortisol peaks for your 24 hour rhythm between 8 and 9 AM on average (Debono et al., 2009). Therefore, you are drinking caffeine at a time when you are already approaching your maximal level of alertness naturally. &lt;em&gt;One of the key principles of pharmacology is use a drug when it is needed&lt;/em&gt; (although I’m sure some scientists might argue that caffeine is always needed). Otherwise, we can develop tolerance to a drug administered at the same dose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you wondering what cortisol is? I did, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.todaysdietitian.com/newarchives/111609p38.shtml"&gt;Cortisol&lt;/a&gt;, a glucocorticoid (steroid hormone), is produced from cholesterol in the two adrenal glands located on top of each kidney. It is normally released in response to events and circumstances such as waking up in the morning, exercising, and acute stress. Cortisol’s far-reaching, systemic effects play many roles in the body’s effort to carry out its processes and maintain homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cortisol is part of the fight-or-flight response. We don’t want too much cortisol, but it’s normal to get a boost of it at specific times, such as waking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with caffeine during peak natural cortisol production is that the body, in effect, says, “Hey, this coffee’s doing a great job! Turn off the cortisol!” Over time, we get less of a boost than we used to, so we drink more coffee. And our body says, “Wow, more coffee? Better turn down the cortisol again!” And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="personal-results"&gt;Personal Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had some trouble in the past getting good, consistent sleep. I can’t blame it all on how I’ve been drinking coffee, but here's my current, typical morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stretch/exercise for about 20 minutes first thing in the morning (7am). This wakes me up &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; better than coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three or four cups of coffee starting about 9:30 (ending before 11:30), and another cup at about 2pm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has changed since adopting this routine is I don't feel I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; coffee first thing in the morning to wake up. And that's because, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don't&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;! If I miss some coffee, it doesn't throw my whole sleeping pattern out of whack, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="other-references"&gt;Other References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/anthonykosner/2014/01/05/why-the-best-time-to-drink-coffee-is-not-first-thing-in-the-morning/#f3c6a327a717"&gt;Why The Best Time To Drink Coffee Is Not First Thing In The Morning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://time.com/3903826/coffee-early-morning-worst-time/"&gt;Coffee: Drinking in the Morning is not the Best Time | Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 15:03:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Open Email to Blackwing602.com About Their Poor Account Security</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/blackwing602.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a Blackwing pencil fan. But I've had some problems with their web site account management. A few days ago I wanted to verify the email address on my account because I kept getting shipping notifications to an old email address. I wasn't able to log in using either email address, and the error message was that &lt;em&gt;there was no such account&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I emailed Blackwing. Here's the reply I received, and my response. I've emphasized the key statement that triggered my response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="blackwing-email"&gt;Blackwing Email&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi Charles,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just sent an account activation email for your Blackwing account, and once you activate that, you should be able to log in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to Pencils.com or Blackwing602.com account changes (such as email address), &lt;strong&gt;only we can change that on our end (for security)&lt;/strong&gt;. If you need us to make adjustments, let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The [-----------] email address is the one that will have the Volumes shipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know about your security concerns on Pencils.com and I can look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had recently switched our sites to Shopify, which is one of the most used ecommerce platforms, and it seems we're just experiencing some growing pains from the move.
Thank you so much for your patience in this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us know if you have any questions! I'm also available via phone at [------------], from 8am-5pm Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-response"&gt;My Response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for sending the link. I've reactivated my account. I need to address several points in your email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volumes Shipment Email&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My email address is [------------]. &lt;em&gt;Please&lt;/em&gt; do whatever you have to to get my shipping notification email changed. The address you're using is old, I haven't used it for two years. I've made this request more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Site Security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm very concerned by your reply on security. I'm a veteran software engineer with twenty-plus years of experience, focused mainly on web applications, so I've had to research and implement web site security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are screen shots of the Blacking602/Pencils account pages. Let's see what customers &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do before discussing what they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be able to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blackwing602&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/blackwing-page-1.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the main page, a customer can only change addresses. Clicking the Edit link opens this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/blackwing-page-2.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's going on here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is a customer changing this information, or creating a new account?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why aren't First and Last name populated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If allowed to change password, why no password confirmation field?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Back or Cancel link, making it obvious the customer can back out of the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't even try to update anything. Based on our conversation, I didn't trust what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want you to read that again. I &lt;strong&gt;didn't trust&lt;/strong&gt; what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pencils&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/pencils-page-1.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this main page, there's not even an edit link to--potentially--allow any account information changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You say in your email, &amp;quot;With regards to Pencils.com or Blackwing602.com account changes (such as email address), only we can change that on our end (for security).&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry to be blunt, but this is dead wrong. It's the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; of good security and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn't user-friendly. At all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say a customer has changed her email address. She's going through all of her sites. She gets to Blackwing/Pencils and doesn't see any way to change her email. She clicks around for a minute. She checks the FAQ. How is she supposed to know that she has to &lt;em&gt;email customer service&lt;/em&gt; to change her information? Well, you could put a message on the account page, with an email link to account_changes@blacking602.com. That would be terrible. What's to prevent a DDoS attack on that link? OK, how about a form requesting the change? So now the user is thinking, &amp;quot;If I'm entering my request for change online anyway, why don't the just automate it?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another situation. A customer has legally changed his/her name. They have to email Blackwing to make that change? What's more likely, in both the above, is the user gives up, doesn't make the change, and eventually stops buying from the company because it was so easy to change at &lt;em&gt;every other business&lt;/em&gt;. He or she had a messy divorce, and doesn't want to be reminded of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn't secure for a user's worst case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submitted my question on May 31. I got your email June 3. That's four days. Let's say a customer finds out he's been hacked. He hasn't been careful, and used the same password at lots of places. Is Blackwing saying he has to wait &lt;em&gt;four days&lt;/em&gt; to get his password changed? The question is the same for changing the email. It's suddenly--for the customer--a security risk, an emergency, and Blackwing is &lt;em&gt;preventing&lt;/em&gt; an immediate change. Even worse, as stated above,  is that the customer has no clue how to even make the change. You just end up with an angry customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It implies poor security, because users are giving their changes to a person whom they don't know they can trust.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I trust you. No, wait...do I? If Blackwing is making me email you to change my account, that means I should trust &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to enter the information more than myself. What if you get my email wrong? It's going to happen. Now I'm locked out of my account &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; I have to email you, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it could be on a weekend when there's no response, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; I was going to order these items for a wedding anniversary gift, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; now they're going to arrive late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see the problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It implies customers should send you their changed passwords. And if they're not, and you're sending them to a password reset form, why not make that available online in the first place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn't scalable in a breach worst case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pencils.com has a security breach. Tens of thousands of passwords have been stolen. What next? First, Pencils does the right thing, of course, and notifies their customers immediately. Then, those customers go to the site to change passwords and/or emails and discover...they can't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so you email everyone a reset link, like you did for me. Thirty percent of your customers don't do the reset and...back to the above. Another twenty percent perform the reset, then decide they want to change their passwords to something stronger, or check on their account info and...find they can't make any changes there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It damages the business's reputation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, if your account maintenance is non-standard, then what else about my account isn't being handled in a standard way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is my password being stored securely (using a one-way hash at minimum).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there auditing of changes in place?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If so, &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; does there need to be auditing in place? Why is any employee able to directly change a user's security information? That is fundamentally insecure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From bad to worse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked above, again, to get my shipping notification email changed. That's bad. It means two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The original request was never honored, so Blackwing's reputation with me is soured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no automated system in place to update the shipping and notification information from the customer account information. And I've experienced this. I have zero confidence that, if I were to change my address online, my shipments would come to my new address. It's failed before, and the changes to account management make me trust the system less, not more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What To Do&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; to consider when it comes to account security (see &lt;em&gt;References&lt;/em&gt;), they are by-and-large known and solved problems. If Pencils/Blacking site developers don't know how, they &lt;em&gt;need to&lt;/em&gt; (not should) hire someone to implement the features properly and securely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the answer to resetting a password (the Forgot Password scenario) is to send a reset URL that's unique to that reset request, and will expire. An answer to changing the email address, which is also the account id, is to likewise send a confirmation URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've spent about an hour and a half on this email, which I've posted to my blog: &lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/"&gt;An Open Email To Blackwing602.Com About Their Poor Account Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a customer, I'd like two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A confirmation you've received and read, even if you don't agree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An assurance this email will be forwarded to the IT and Sales directors. IT because it's a security issue, and Sales because it's a customer-retention issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the positive side, I truly do love my Blackwings, and am grateful the brand was revived. I'm asking you to be the messenger--I don't consider you responsible for these problems, and I value your courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just two discussions, from security expert Troy Hunt, of the problems of web site security. But notice that &amp;quot;don't allow changes&amp;quot; never comes up as a solution. Because it isn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/everything-you-ever-wanted-to-know/"&gt;Troy Hunt: Everything you ever wanted to know about building a secure password reset feature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/introducing-secure-account-management/"&gt;Troy Hunt: Introducing the “Secure Account Management Fundamentals” course on Pluralsight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles L Flatt&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 4 Jun 2019 11:06:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>