<?xml version="1.0" encoding ="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Meadows</title>
    <description>A pleasant walk through computing</description>
    <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/feed</link>
    <link href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" />
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Sugar: 'Accelerate', the Best Book About DevOps</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/devops/accelerate_notes_and_quotes/accelerate-header.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I run a Meetup called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Coffee-Quiet-Code/"&gt;Coffee. Quiet. Code.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I want to encourage developers to work together in the same casual space without having to discuss anything or even interact much. It could be seen as a far less rigid version of Mycroft Holmes' &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diogenes_Club"&gt;&amp;quot;Dionysus Club&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, a way to enjoy shared community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My inspiration came from people, often strangers, reading together in libraries, and also the sweet memories of my whole family reading their separate books they received as holiday gifts. In that spirit, here's a book recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Accelerate-Software-Performing-Technology-Organizations-ebook/dp/B07B9F83WM"&gt;Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps&lt;/a&gt; is exactly what it claims to be: high-quality, peer-reviewed research answering the practical question &amp;quot;What's really working in software development across all industries and team sizes?&amp;quot; There are plenty of opinions out there on DevOps. This book deals in facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote an extensive book summary for a client, which you'll find on my web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/devops/accelerate_notes_and_quotes/"&gt;'Accelerate' Book Notes And Quotes | Software Meadows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 14:02:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_accelerate__the_best_book_about_devops</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_accelerate__the_best_book_about_devops</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flatt's Posts/Casts Review #003 - Incentives, Emotions, Diversity, and Applying Bodyguard Training to Coding</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/20190616-1610 flatts_posts-casts_review_003/../images/reviews-logo.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019-05-23 to 2019-06-16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still in the discovery period for how to present my summaries of the articles and podcasts I read over a period of time. While I'm hoping the information is useful to others, it's primarily for me to A) continue learning, and B) look for essential patters in the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I'm going to present what I think are the top-level ideas across &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the material, and the top ideas for each episode. This should make the information easier to digest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, since I highlighted it in the title, here's the link and notes on the Bodyguard podcast and how I'd apply them to development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/podcast-513-be-your-own-bodyguard/"&gt;Art of Manliness #513 Be Your Own Bodyguard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These are self-defence principles, and apply to potentially dangerous situations. &lt;strong&gt;But note how they also apply to coding!&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoidance is the most important thing you can practice. (&lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deescalation is the next most important. (&lt;strong&gt;find/fix bugs fast&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where are your exits? (&lt;strong&gt;version control&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IF there's a fight, what are your three or four &amp;quot;go to techniques you practice all the time&amp;quot;? (&lt;strong&gt;logging, alerts, debugging&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regularly simulate and practice stress situations in class. (&lt;strong&gt;disaster testing&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn from people who've experienced it. (&lt;strong&gt;involve users&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the legal impact?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="essential-learnings"&gt;Essential Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align incentives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotions drive our decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study multiple subjects (generalize) and apply to your specialty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversity is highly beneficial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.leadingagile.com/podcast/what-is-a-well-formed-backlog/"&gt;Leading Agile - What is a Well-Formed Backlog? w/ Jeff Howey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating clear characteristics of a well-formed backlog is valuable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the criteria simple and short as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the terms and make sure everyone understands them. (Publish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Howey's characterstics: Clearly Prioritized, Linked to What's Important, Shared Understanding, Identify Dependencies, Clear Acceptance Criteria, Clear Definitions of &amp;quot;Done&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Ready&amp;quot;, Good Enough to Start a Conversation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/psychology-of-investing/"&gt;Art of Manliness #511: Mastering the Psychology of Investing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We think bad things happening are dramatically less likely than good things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The more complex and dynamic a system is, the more simple your solution needs to be.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;There's a weak correlation between knowing the right thing to do and actually doing it.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our decisions are strongly influenced by our bodies and emotions. Don't code upset!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humans are terrible at probability. They tend to reason in group terms, and conform to the group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/generalist-specialist-david-epstein-interview/"&gt;Art of Manliness #512: Why Generalists Triumph in a Specialized World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tiger Woods specialized. Roger Federer generalized until his twenties when he settled on tennis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;quot;ten thousand hours to become an expert&amp;quot; research examined specific fields that, it turns out, yield well to early specializing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the time kids are better off delaying specialization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generalists are better at new situations because they can synthesize and apply previous experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299506"&gt;Developer Tea - Mental Models w/Gabriel Weinberg Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299507"&gt;Developer Tea - Mental Models w/Gabriel Weinberg Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book of 300 mental models, i.e. &amp;quot;fancy word for concepts&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Models Weinberg thinks managers/developers often miss:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunity Costs: &amp;quot;The cost of what you're working on is what you're not working on.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing Function: &amp;quot;Scheduled process to force everyone to think critically.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find root cause using the Five Whys Model, asking &amp;quot;why?&amp;quot; until getting to the root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;I want to do this thing not because it's imporant, but because it's more important that all these other things.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299950"&gt;Developer Tea - 3 Assumptions That Can Hurt Your Job Search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you get turned down that means you are incapable of doing that job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone is going to read your whole resume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications to jobs are how people get jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Imagine you're trying to find a job without job boards being available. What else can you do to find a job?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299948"&gt;Developer Tea - Aligning Incentives w/ Lambda School CTO - Ben Nelson (part 1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/299949"&gt;Developer Tea - Aligning Incentives w/ Lambda School CTO - Ben Nelson (part 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lambda School doesn't charge tuition for its education, and only makes money when its graduates get a job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very high bar for getting in. They're looking for grit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incentive Alignment. Both sides are working toward the same goal, and only succeed if the goal is achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hanselminutes.com/687/how-to-build-an-inclusive-conference-with-saron-yitbarek"&gt;Hanselminutes: How to build an inclusive conference with Saron Yitbarek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://codelandconf.com/"&gt;Codeland Conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yitbarek's goal in the conference is to celebrate coding, not the tools, and to be the most inclusive conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She mentions a study of people who do/don't finish computer science degrees. Those who do have a higher threshold for confusion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gimletmedia.com/shows/science-vs/awhklj"&gt;Science Vs. - How Bad Science Killed A President&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garfield died two and a half months after being shot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Among those who tried to help were Alexander Graham Bell with a new invention: a metal detector!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite Joseph Lister lecturing about bacteria and how to kill them for five years, doctors still don't believe it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So, basically, the doctors are digging around in Garfield's body with grubby hands, causing infection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nine years later, partly due to Garfield's death, doctors believe in germs and are sterilizing everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.growthmindsetpodcast.com/blog/2019/scott-brinker"&gt;Growth Mindset #59 - The World of Martech - Scott Brinker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One interesting comment was that Brinker thought marketers had an easier time experimenting--such as using A-B testing--that developers. (He was talking about the idea of Agile Marketing.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/300682"&gt;Developer Tea - Test Driven Meetings - Measuring Outputs and Side Effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at a meeting as if it's made up of methods. A one-on-one meeting might have a &amp;quot;feedback function,&amp;quot; which is a unit test idea. So look at the inputs and outputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But we also want to look at meetings as integration tests. What are the side effects, both positive and negative?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here's what Jonathan suggests in trying to apply the idea
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before the meeting, write down the outputs and the side effects that you desire from the meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Announce the outcome(s) and side effect(s) at the top of meeting so everyone is oriented toward them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/aristotle-living-the-good-life/"&gt;Art of Manliness #515 - Aristotle's Wisdom on Living the Good Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://edithhall.co.uk/"&gt;Edith Hall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0735220808/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0735220808&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=stucosuccess&amp;amp;linkId=FSXA3GZUT5SFDAZ4"&gt;Aristotle’s Way: How Ancient Wisdom Can Change Your Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aristotle wanted people to find their telos (purpose). Hall thinks today's education reduces the variety of exposure kids get to things like the arts, reducing their ability to find their telos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/300990"&gt;Developer Tea - How Can Two Rational People Disagree?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the same data, the frame parameters are different.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: Choosing between a bug or feature. Developer says feature because his frame is long-term. Manager says bug because his frame is short-term. Both are rationally good choices given the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often, in conflict, desires and incentives are the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.growthmindsetpodcast.com/blog/2019/niall-mccann"&gt;Growth Mindset - Doing the Difficult Thing - Dr Niall McCann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspiring and humbling. The guy's amazing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out what motivates those who can help you attain your goal, AND&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align their incentives to yours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do what you're doing first because you enjoy it. But also show how success has layers of benefits. Example: McCann's organization protecting a swathe of land not only prevented mass killing of elephants, but also raised local employment, the success increased donorship, and tourism increased because the animals were there to be seen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're not really a conservationist unless you've &lt;em&gt;conserved&lt;/em&gt; something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/podcast-516-how-to-lead-an-unstoppable-team/"&gt;Art of Manliness #516 - How to Lead an Unstoppable Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://alden-mills.com/"&gt;Alden Mills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0062876155/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0062876155&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=stucosuccess&amp;amp;linkId=FSXA3GZUT5SFDAZ4"&gt;Unstoppable Teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mills is fantastically clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to lead yourself first before you can lead others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a team means building relationships, which involves feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CARE Loop
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect&lt;/strong&gt; The real goal in connecting is to build trust.&lt;br /&gt;
Three tools: communication, commitment, credibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Achieve&lt;/strong&gt; Set direction.&lt;br /&gt;
Five A's: Aspiring (which he's using like &amp;quot;inspiring&amp;quot;), Assume they can do the job, Assess what they're doing, Appreciate their efforts internally and externally, and ????&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respect&lt;/strong&gt; Goal of respect is contribution, and requires mutual respect. To get everyone contributing their ideas, skills, etc.&lt;br /&gt;
Want people to be willing to say &amp;quot;I made a mistake,&amp;quot; then answer three questions: what happened, what I was trying to achieve, what I'm going to do about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empower&lt;/strong&gt; Getting people to think like owners.&lt;br /&gt;
Three Es: Educating, Enabling, Engaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gimletmedia.com/shows/science-vs/brh824"&gt;Sciene Vs. - SHARKS!!!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top speed of Great Whites, in just a couple of tail flicks, from 1mph to 25mph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sharks &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; smell blood in an Olympic-size swimming pool. They smell as well as other fish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From 2010-2012, more people died from TVs tipping over onto them (51) than from shark attacks (3). 124 shark bites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no such thing as a rogue shark (like &lt;em&gt;Jaws&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One quarter of shark species are threatened with extinction...including the Great White.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dotnetcore.show/episode-27-blazroed-with-chris-sainty/"&gt;.NET Core Podcast #27 - Blazored with Chris Sainty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chrissainty.com/"&gt;Chris Sainty - Building with Blazor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Blazored"&gt;Blazored&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What's so great about Blazor?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to write truly full stack applications using just C#&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opens up using NuGet instead of waiting for a new javascript framework's ecosystem to build up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On security of running a C# dll in the browser, Chris points out WebAssembly runs in the same sandbox as javascript. So, no more or less secure than javascript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But, it's still in early development. Not ready for general production use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we take on a dependency into our applications, if you're taking on someone else's code, you're always taking on a level of risk, and it's up to you to assess that level and go from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 16:13:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/20190616-1610 flatts_posts-casts_review_003</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/20190616-1610 flatts_posts-casts_review_003</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Sugar: Applying Kanban Principles to Your Personal Task List</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_applying_kanban_principles_to_your_personal_task_list/images/vertical-task-list.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us use Kanban boards (or you might be calling them Scrum boards) on work projects. And, we might use &lt;a href="https://trello.com/"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; for some home projects. But most people probably &lt;em&gt;aren't&lt;/em&gt; using them for their daily task lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of To Do apps out there, but here's a &amp;quot;first principles&amp;quot; approach using two lists. I do this in &lt;a href="http://keep.google.com"&gt;Google Keep&lt;/a&gt;, but it could as easily be done on paper, which is the inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;TODAY
- [ ] Finish base page
- [ ] Start home controllers
- [ ] Buy diapers at lunch

WAITING ON
- [ ] Time approval from Florence (emailed 5/12 3p)

SOON (limit 5)
- [ ] Read *Accelerate*
- [ ] Prepare for DevOps conference
- [ ] Call Marcus about tennis Thu
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;PERSONAL BACKLOG
- [ ] Plan Vinit's birthday
- [ ] Add user stories to MyCoolProject  
etc.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Keep, or a text file, it's easy to move tasks around. On paper, you might write in pencil and renumber priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, this is the same as a Kanban flow, just rotated 90 degrees. It's easy to update and change, which is critical to capturing thoughts quickly so they don't get lost. The software (or hardware) gets out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 11:34:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_applying_kanban_principles_to_your_personal_task_list</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_applying_kanban_principles_to_your_personal_task_list</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joe Developer: When (not) to Drink Coffee</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee/images/coffee-clock.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-06-10 15:03:00 This is an update of an article I wrote a few years ago.&lt;br /&gt;
2019-06-11 09:25:38 Significant update to call out when to drink coffee and other health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-gist"&gt;The Gist&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should drink coffee between 9:30 and 11:30, and &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; also between 1:30 and 5:00.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drinking 4-5 8oz cups per day has other health benefits. Quoted:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of cancer up to 20 percent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of heart disease by 5 percent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of Type 2 diabetes by 30 percent; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces your risk of Parkinson's disease by 30 percent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unless you're pregnant. If pregnant, coffee can slightly increase the risk of miscarriage.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science shows drinking coffee first thing in the morning negatively affects one’s circadian rhythm by inhibiting the production of cortisol, which the body uses to naturally wake us up. Drinking coffee when cortisol levels are falling helps us stay evenly alert. The recommended times are based on the average person who gets up around 6:30am. Adjust accordingly for your own consistent wake time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best summary for both time-of-day and health benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/geoffrey-james/scientists-just-discovered-best-time-of-day-to-drink-your-first-cup-of-coffee.html"&gt;The Best Time of Day to Drink Coffee, According to Science | Inc.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most entertaining summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.ilovecoffee.jp/posts/view/57"&gt;The best time to drink coffee according to science - I Love Coffee&lt;/a&gt; (with infographics!!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last entry seems to have begat many others. It’s my favorite. It makes me happy to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee/images/2019-06-11_09-38-22.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these articles discusses &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to shift your coffee consumption, which is a shame. It's like telling a smoker, &amp;quot;just quit.&amp;quot; The thing is, cortisol production doesn't just leap back into action. I've taken &lt;a href="https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-22008/budesonide-oral/details"&gt;budesonide&lt;/a&gt;, which decreases cortisol production, and the weaning off period is 2-4 weeks. So, I recommend making the change gradually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-article-trail"&gt;The Article Trail&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first read &lt;a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3034375/coffee-week/the-new-habit-challenge-drink-your-coffee-when-science-tells-you-to"&gt;this 2014 article&lt;/a&gt; about why you shouldn’t drink coffee first thing in the morning, i.e. right after getting up. Curious, I tried to find out more on the subject. I turned out there are several similar articles. In all cases, the stories originate from an article by Steven Miller, Ph.D., &lt;a href="http://neurosciencedc.blogspot.jp/2013/10/the-best-time-for-your-coffee.html"&gt;The Best Time for Your Coffee&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Dr Miller is a scientist, and he cites his sources, and he’s clear about what he’s saying and not saying. Check out the comments on his article; he defends against a few hostile readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where did he get his data? That’s from a study in 2009, the sciency-named &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2684472/"&gt;Modified-Release Hydrocortisone to Provide Circadian Cortisol Profiles&lt;/a&gt;. This article, which has 80% words I don’t understand, includes this graphic showing natural peak cortisol levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee/images/ScreenCap_2019-06-10_15-21-37.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="whats-what"&gt;What’s What?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Miller doesn’t point to a specific study proving that people should drink coffee at a particular time. He states his opinion based on the research. I liked his interesting pharmacological approach (emphases are mine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drug tolerance is an important subject, especially in the case of caffeine since &lt;em&gt;most of us overuse this drug&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, if we are drinking caffeine at a time when your cortisol concentration in the blood is at its peak, you probably should not be drinking it. This is because cortisol production is strongly related to your level of alertness and it just so happens that cortisol peaks for your 24 hour rhythm between 8 and 9 AM on average (Debono et al., 2009). Therefore, you are drinking caffeine at a time when you are already approaching your maximal level of alertness naturally. &lt;em&gt;One of the key principles of pharmacology is use a drug when it is needed&lt;/em&gt; (although I’m sure some scientists might argue that caffeine is always needed). Otherwise, we can develop tolerance to a drug administered at the same dose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you wondering what cortisol is? I did, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.todaysdietitian.com/newarchives/111609p38.shtml"&gt;Cortisol&lt;/a&gt;, a glucocorticoid (steroid hormone), is produced from cholesterol in the two adrenal glands located on top of each kidney. It is normally released in response to events and circumstances such as waking up in the morning, exercising, and acute stress. Cortisol’s far-reaching, systemic effects play many roles in the body’s effort to carry out its processes and maintain homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cortisol is part of the fight-or-flight response. We don’t want too much cortisol, but it’s normal to get a boost of it at specific times, such as waking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with caffeine during peak natural cortisol production is that the body, in effect, says, “Hey, this coffee’s doing a great job! Turn off the cortisol!” Over time, we get less of a boost than we used to, so we drink more coffee. And our body says, “Wow, more coffee? Better turn down the cortisol again!” And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="personal-results"&gt;Personal Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had some trouble in the past getting good, consistent sleep. I can’t blame it all on how I’ve been drinking coffee, but here's my current, typical morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stretch/exercise for about 20 minutes first thing in the morning (7am). This wakes me up &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; better than coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three or four cups of coffee starting about 9:30 (ending before 11:30), and another cup at about 2pm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has changed since adopting this routine is I don't feel I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; coffee first thing in the morning to wake up. And that's because, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don't&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;! If I miss some coffee, it doesn't throw my whole sleeping pattern out of whack, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="other-references"&gt;Other References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/anthonykosner/2014/01/05/why-the-best-time-to-drink-coffee-is-not-first-thing-in-the-morning/#f3c6a327a717"&gt;Why The Best Time To Drink Coffee Is Not First Thing In The Morning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://time.com/3903826/coffee-early-morning-worst-time/"&gt;Coffee: Drinking in the Morning is not the Best Time | Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 15:03:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/joe_developer-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffee</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Open Email to Blackwing602.com About Their Poor Account Security</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/blackwing602.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a Blackwing pencil fan. But I've had some problems with their web site account management. A few days ago I wanted to verify the email address on my account because I kept getting shipping notifications to an old email address. I wasn't able to log in using either email address, and the error message was that &lt;em&gt;there was no such account&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I emailed Blackwing. Here's the reply I received, and my response. I've emphasized the key statement that triggered my response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="blackwing-email"&gt;Blackwing Email&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi Charles,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just sent an account activation email for your Blackwing account, and once you activate that, you should be able to log in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to Pencils.com or Blackwing602.com account changes (such as email address), &lt;strong&gt;only we can change that on our end (for security)&lt;/strong&gt;. If you need us to make adjustments, let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The [-----------] email address is the one that will have the Volumes shipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know about your security concerns on Pencils.com and I can look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had recently switched our sites to Shopify, which is one of the most used ecommerce platforms, and it seems we're just experiencing some growing pains from the move.
Thank you so much for your patience in this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us know if you have any questions! I'm also available via phone at [------------], from 8am-5pm Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-response"&gt;My Response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for sending the link. I've reactivated my account. I need to address several points in your email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volumes Shipment Email&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My email address is [------------]. &lt;em&gt;Please&lt;/em&gt; do whatever you have to to get my shipping notification email changed. The address you're using is old, I haven't used it for two years. I've made this request more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Site Security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm very concerned by your reply on security. I'm a veteran software engineer with twenty-plus years of experience, focused mainly on web applications, so I've had to research and implement web site security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are screen shots of the Blacking602/Pencils account pages. Let's see what customers &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do before discussing what they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be able to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blackwing602&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/blackwing-page-1.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the main page, a customer can only change addresses. Clicking the Edit link opens this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/blackwing-page-2.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's going on here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is a customer changing this information, or creating a new account?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why aren't First and Last name populated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If allowed to change password, why no password confirmation field?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Back or Cancel link, making it obvious the customer can back out of the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't even try to update anything. Based on our conversation, I didn't trust what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want you to read that again. I &lt;strong&gt;didn't trust&lt;/strong&gt; what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pencils&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/images/pencils-page-1.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this main page, there's not even an edit link to--potentially--allow any account information changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You say in your email, &amp;quot;With regards to Pencils.com or Blackwing602.com account changes (such as email address), only we can change that on our end (for security).&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry to be blunt, but this is dead wrong. It's the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; of good security and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn't user-friendly. At all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say a customer has changed her email address. She's going through all of her sites. She gets to Blackwing/Pencils and doesn't see any way to change her email. She clicks around for a minute. She checks the FAQ. How is she supposed to know that she has to &lt;em&gt;email customer service&lt;/em&gt; to change her information? Well, you could put a message on the account page, with an email link to account_changes@blacking602.com. That would be terrible. What's to prevent a DDoS attack on that link? OK, how about a form requesting the change? So now the user is thinking, &amp;quot;If I'm entering my request for change online anyway, why don't the just automate it?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another situation. A customer has legally changed his/her name. They have to email Blackwing to make that change? What's more likely, in both the above, is the user gives up, doesn't make the change, and eventually stops buying from the company because it was so easy to change at &lt;em&gt;every other business&lt;/em&gt;. He or she had a messy divorce, and doesn't want to be reminded of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn't secure for a user's worst case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submitted my question on May 31. I got your email June 3. That's four days. Let's say a customer finds out he's been hacked. He hasn't been careful, and used the same password at lots of places. Is Blackwing saying he has to wait &lt;em&gt;four days&lt;/em&gt; to get his password changed? The question is the same for changing the email. It's suddenly--for the customer--a security risk, an emergency, and Blackwing is &lt;em&gt;preventing&lt;/em&gt; an immediate change. Even worse, as stated above,  is that the customer has no clue how to even make the change. You just end up with an angry customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It implies poor security, because users are giving their changes to a person whom they don't know they can trust.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I trust you. No, wait...do I? If Blackwing is making me email you to change my account, that means I should trust &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to enter the information more than myself. What if you get my email wrong? It's going to happen. Now I'm locked out of my account &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; I have to email you, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it could be on a weekend when there's no response, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; I was going to order these items for a wedding anniversary gift, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; now they're going to arrive late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see the problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It implies customers should send you their changed passwords. And if they're not, and you're sending them to a password reset form, why not make that available online in the first place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn't scalable in a breach worst case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pencils.com has a security breach. Tens of thousands of passwords have been stolen. What next? First, Pencils does the right thing, of course, and notifies their customers immediately. Then, those customers go to the site to change passwords and/or emails and discover...they can't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so you email everyone a reset link, like you did for me. Thirty percent of your customers don't do the reset and...back to the above. Another twenty percent perform the reset, then decide they want to change their passwords to something stronger, or check on their account info and...find they can't make any changes there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It damages the business's reputation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, if your account maintenance is non-standard, then what else about my account isn't being handled in a standard way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is my password being stored securely (using a one-way hash at minimum).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there auditing of changes in place?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If so, &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; does there need to be auditing in place? Why is any employee able to directly change a user's security information? That is fundamentally insecure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From bad to worse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked above, again, to get my shipping notification email changed. That's bad. It means two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The original request was never honored, so Blackwing's reputation with me is soured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no automated system in place to update the shipping and notification information from the customer account information. And I've experienced this. I have zero confidence that, if I were to change my address online, my shipments would come to my new address. It's failed before, and the changes to account management make me trust the system less, not more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What To Do&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; to consider when it comes to account security (see &lt;em&gt;References&lt;/em&gt;), they are by-and-large known and solved problems. If Pencils/Blacking site developers don't know how, they &lt;em&gt;need to&lt;/em&gt; (not should) hire someone to implement the features properly and securely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the answer to resetting a password (the Forgot Password scenario) is to send a reset URL that's unique to that reset request, and will expire. An answer to changing the email address, which is also the account id, is to likewise send a confirmation URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've spent about an hour and a half on this email, which I've posted to my blog: &lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security/"&gt;An Open Email To Blackwing602.Com About Their Poor Account Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a customer, I'd like two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A confirmation you've received and read, even if you don't agree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An assurance this email will be forwarded to the IT and Sales directors. IT because it's a security issue, and Sales because it's a customer-retention issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the positive side, I truly do love my Blackwings, and am grateful the brand was revived. I'm asking you to be the messenger--I don't consider you responsible for these problems, and I value your courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just two discussions, from security expert Troy Hunt, of the problems of web site security. But notice that &amp;quot;don't allow changes&amp;quot; never comes up as a solution. Because it isn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/everything-you-ever-wanted-to-know/"&gt;Troy Hunt: Everything you ever wanted to know about building a secure password reset feature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.troyhunt.com/introducing-secure-account-management/"&gt;Troy Hunt: Introducing the “Secure Account Management Fundamentals” course on Pluralsight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles L Flatt&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 4 Jun 2019 11:06:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/an_open_email_to_blackwing602_com_about_their_poor_account_security</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Sugar: Take a Walk</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_take_a_walk/walking-man.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You've been stuck on a thorny problem for an hour, and the forehead-shaped dents on your desk are going to upset the maintenance department--again. You're about to run out of coffee. The problem is attached to you like a &lt;a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/39/20000_squid_Nautilus_viewbay.jpg"&gt;squid on the Nautilus&lt;/a&gt;. What's the next step?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science says the next step is, literally, steps. Take a break and walk. Eyes off screen, don't read your phone. Go outside if you can. The &amp;quot;extra&amp;quot; ten minutes will often save another hour of struggle as you give your brain a chance to do what it's good at: reforming patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it today. Stop. Breathe. Take a walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://scienceline.org/2014/11/stuck-on-a-problem-take-a-walk/"&gt;Stuck on a problem? Take a walk | Scienceline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 3 Jun 2019 09:39:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_take_a_walk</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_take_a_walk</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Response to Jonathan Cutrell's Podcast Episode "Crafting Your Work By Your Strengths"</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_response_to_jonathan_cutrells_podcast_episode_crafting_your_work_b/images/high-kick.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Karate_WM_2014_(2)_019.JPG"&gt;File:Karate WM 2014 (2) 019.JPG - Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="up-front"&gt;Up Front&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always look forward to Jonathan's podcast, and rarely find myself critical, but I found &lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/298944"&gt;this episode&lt;/a&gt; somewhat unclear and unfocused. I'd like to help clarify what I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; Jonathan wanted to promote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-points"&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map your skill/knowledge strengths/weaknesses to the job's required core/ancillary skills/knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve your weaknesses that are in the job's core.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve your strengths that are in the job's core.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't &lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/browse/deprecate"&gt;deprecate&lt;/a&gt; yourself for weaknesses and mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="discussion"&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As developers, workers, and people, we're faced with deciding whether to improve our weaknesses or our strengths, and which ones. We &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to do both. Focusing on only one or the other is unlikely to lead to success. There's science supporting that only repeating what you're good at doesn't lead to improvement. However, only working on what you're not good at leads to atrophy of your strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a martial artist. If my left side kicks aren't as good as my right side kicks, then I need to work harder at my left ones. There's an implicit goal of parity. However, we sometimes forget (as students and teachers) that the purpose of that goal is improvement, not achievement. It's OK if my left side kicks are never as good as my right ones. It's also OK if I work hard to make my right kicks amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But--to continue the analogy--should I focus on being able to side kick to someone's head who is over six feet tall &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; hold that kick in place? Some kata competition champions can do this. It's their strength. It's not mine. The short answer is &amp;quot;no,&amp;quot; because &lt;em&gt;this is important in the context of competition, but not in my interest which is daily health and self-defense.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that context, let's go back to the podcast and pull the benefit from it. What's a way to help clarify which job skills we should improve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create two lists. One is your skill/knowledge strengths and weaknesses. The other is the job's required core and ancillary skills/knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skill/Knowledge Lists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;( * &lt;em&gt;Starred items are ones I'm naturally good at.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ME&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;JOB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tenacity*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;System Organization*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Customer requirements gathering&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Understanding Customers' Needs*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;REST-ful APIs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Scalable architecture&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WebAPI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Documentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weak&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancillary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Self-confidence&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Employee management&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proven scalability experience&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Documentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Python&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To meet the job's needs, we should always work on the core skills. Give these lists, here's what I'd recommend the fictitious developer focus on improving:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C#, keep improving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer needs, leverage your strength into becoming an expert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebApi, keep improving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalable architecture, work hard at improving this weakness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don't spend much time on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System organization, Tenacity, or Documentation, you're already good enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personnel management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrap-up"&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really think this is the essence of what Jonathan was trying to say, but--unusually--the message got lost on a first listen. I'd say a few lesser episodes out of almost seven hundred is pretty darn good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Jonathan!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 10:57:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_response_to_jonathan_cutrells_podcast_episode_crafting_your_work_b</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_response_to_jonathan_cutrells_podcast_episode_crafting_your_work_b</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weekly Sugar: When (not) to Drink Coffee, a Preview</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffe__a_preview/images/coffee-clock.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago I researched and posted about when--and when not--to drink coffee. I'm going to repost that article to &lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com"&gt;https://www.softwaremeadows.com&lt;/a&gt; in the next several days. Until then, then gist is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science shows drinking coffee first thing in the morning negatively affects one’s circadian rhythm by inhibiting the production of cortisol, which the body uses to naturally wake us up. Instead, we should drink coffee between 9:30 and 11:30, and maybe also between 1:30 and 5:00, when cortisol levels are falling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I drink my morning coffee at least one hour after waking up, which is also supported by the research)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 14:40:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffe__a_preview</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/weekly_sugar-_when_(not)_to_drink_coffe__a_preview</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flatt's Posts/Casts Review #002 - Real Problems, Strengths, Korean War, Smaller Problems, Good/Bad Shame</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/flatts_posts-casts_review_002_-_real_problems__strengths__korean_war/../images/reviews-logo.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each week I'll try to post summaries, notes and quotes about articles I've read and podcasts I've listened to during the week. This helps me pay closer attention to the material, and may help you decide if you want to go to the source--which I hope you do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#art-of-manliness-509-good-shame-bad-shame"&gt;Art of Manliness #509 - Good Shame; Bad Shame&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#developer-tea-20190522-make-your-problems-smaller"&gt;Developer Tea 20190522 - Make Your Problems Smaller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#art-of-manliness-510-the-greatest-battle-of-the-korean-war"&gt;Art of Manliness #510 - The Greatest Battle of the Korean War&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#developer-tea-20190524-crafting-your-work-by-your-strengths"&gt;Developer Tea 20190524 - Crafting Your Work By Your Strengths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#hanselminutes-685-solving-real-problems-with-software-and-the-human-utility-with-tiffani-ashley-bell"&gt;Hanselminutes #685 - Solving real problems with software and the Human Utility with Tiffani Ashley Bell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="art-of-manliness-509-good-shame-bad-shame"&gt;Art of Manliness #509 - Good Shame; Bad Shame&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/shame/"&gt;https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/shame/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-05-20 22:25&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developer Field Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Good&amp;quot; shame promotes shared socially acceptable behavior, and has the possibility of redemption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Bad&amp;quot; shame is cruel and negates who the person is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discover, recognize, and accept your own (and others') limitations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Men and women have, according to science, actual differences. Learn which are real vs societal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About the evolution of masculine and feminine traits: &amp;quot;you can't shame that out of existence.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interview with Joseph Burgo, PhD, author of &lt;em&gt;Shame&lt;/em&gt;. The author's thesis is that there is a spectrum of shame, and that certain types of shame can be valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Categories of Shame:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unrequited love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exclusion (from the group)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unwanted exposure (public embarrassment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disappointed expectation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A potential value of shame is to &amp;quot;promote social values that are shared&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brains have critical periods for formation, and if a child doesn't get the love, etc. that's needed, &amp;quot;you can't make up for it entirely in later life.&amp;quot; They can grow and compensate, but it's within the limits of their early experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burgo makes the case for a couple of socially uncomfortable ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people can't be whatever they want to be. They'll be restricted by limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Men and women are truly genetically different, and trying to force men (in this case) to be the same as women leads to men rebelling and demonstrating even uglier, extreme &amp;quot;manly&amp;quot; behaviors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burgo says there's been a trend since the 60s to create a gender-neutral society, that &amp;quot;men and women should express the same basic positive traits...there is no difference.&amp;quot; Burgo doesn't believe that, and says the science doesn't support that view. About the evolution of masculine and feminine traits, &amp;quot;you can't shame that out of existence.&amp;quot; This is an important point, and I think it's the same science-based understanding of why homosexuality and transgender also must not be shamed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(However, I hate using a computer metaphor when it comes to biology. People aren't computers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way people deal with early core shame is to become narcissists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still hard for men to admit they need--and accept help. It's socially not considered manly. It's even worse in other countries (he cites India).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Positive&amp;quot; shaming must not be cruel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's better to be honest about the way our pasts ...can place limits on our future. It's better to take those limitations into account rather than pretending their are no limitations then failing and feeling even more shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sad science shows that children who grow up with parents who don't love them have brains--their brains are different.... Alan Shore shows brain scans of children who grow up in normal environments and those who grow up in really deficient ones, and [the children in deficient evironments] brains are smaller, they have fewer neural connections, they're just visibly different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The so-called &amp;quot;slacker&amp;quot; personality is organized around avoiding shame. It doesn't look that way, it looks like they don't have any ambition, but that's not really the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Shaming] can be a good thing if it promotes more socially acceptable behavior. In order to do that, it has to hold out the possiblity of redemption. It has to be &amp;quot;you should feel ashamed of this, and your shaming experience is going to have this duration, and we expect you to make amends and then change your behavior.&amp;quot; That's the only way shame is ever effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.josephburgo.com/"&gt;Joseph Burgo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1250151309/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1250151309&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=stucosuccess&amp;amp;linkId=FSXA3GZUT5SFDAZ4"&gt;Shame: Free Yourself, Find Joy, and Build True Self-Esteem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="developer-tea-20190522-make-your-problems-smaller"&gt;Developer Tea 20190522 - Make Your Problems Smaller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/298464"&gt;https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/298464&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-05-22 19:14&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developer Field Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When facing any item of work, ask if it can be broken into simpler components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, elimate the parts that don't matter until finding what's essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth. --Sherlock Holmes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Reducing tasks into smaller tasks is well known in software, and in general productivity. Not as well known, I think, is applying this approach to solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I'm seeing there's an obvious--yet overlooked--generalized pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When facing any item of work, ask if it can be broken into simpler components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, elimate the parts that don't matter until finding what's essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In software, this principle applies to User Stories, architecture, methods, problems, debuggin, and tasks. In habit-forming (and breaking), examining the desired habit and finding the chain of triggers leading to that habit allows you to target the earliest trigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like his coding examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During a debugging session where problem seems to keep moving around, eliminate all the code that &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; part of a function or function call. This lets you see just what's calling what.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a syntax error: eliminate code by halves until error goes away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done number two. Number one is a very interesting idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle is also stated in Sherlock Holmes' famous maxims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have eliminated the impossible, whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this quote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having gathered these facts, Watson, I smoked several pipes over them, trying to separate those which were crucial from others which were merely incidental.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often the problems that we're trying to solve are not actually singular problems. This is true both in our code and our relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complexity of a given problem is first of all hard to define, but secondly it's often undertated. How many factors affecte that problem in the first place, and can you even go back and simulate the problem that occurred? Or maybe you have a difficult decision to make. How can you possibly understand all the factors related to that decision?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you look at every problem as it stands, in the context of the world, in the context of the universe, then of course it's prohibitively difficult to answer these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can easily become crippled by our problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="art-of-manliness-510-the-greatest-battle-of-the-korean-war"&gt;Art of Manliness #510 - The Greatest Battle of the Korean War&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/chosin-reservoir-battle-korean-war/"&gt;https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/chosin-reservoir-battle-korean-war/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-05-24 22:24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development Field Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen to your &amp;quot;people in the field.&amp;quot; These can be direct reports, customers and users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surround yourself with people who will respectfully disagree, when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay honestly humble. Find ways to keep your ego in check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What often surpises me about AoM episodes is that I expect to be either bored or think &amp;quot;ugh, this is not my kind of subject.&amp;quot; Neither has ever true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take this episode. I'm not big on war history, and it seems like a stereotypical thing to talk about on a &amp;quot;manliness&amp;quot; show. I keep forgetting that AoM questions stereotypes in favor of finding a better truth about what it means to be manly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hampton Sides wrote a book on and discusses the events surrounding the Battle of the Chosin Reservoir and the Marines who dubbed themselves the &amp;quot;Frozen Chosin.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote is terrific, so I'm putting it near the top. It's one of the biggest lessons from the conflict, in the author's view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep a channel of communication from the bottom up, not just from the top down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After WWII, Korea was divided in half, the north going to the Soviet Union under Stalin, and the south to the US under Truman. Both were supposed to be temporary. There was supposed to be reunification and an election, but that didn't happen, and the result of each country's influence is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacArthur's mistake, coming out of his hubris, ego, and willful ignorance, was to not stop at the 38th Parallel and instead push further in--under the pretense of making sure it wouldn't happen again--triggering China to get involved because the US would become so close to their border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The description of MacArthur...at this point in his career...is strikingly similar to Donald Trump.&lt;a id="fnref:1" href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. About MacArthur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People didn't know how to handle his personality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCarthyism had risen, and Truman/Democrats were being accused of being soft on Communism. (today it's being soft on immigration.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refused to believe the intelligence reports that China had entered the conflict. Some of his lieutenants doctored the reports (the &amp;quot;yes men&amp;quot; problem, ensuring MacArthur heard what he wanted to hear.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Didn't listen to General Smith, his commander on the ground. (Trump famously says he knows more than his generals.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a fascinating segment giving credit to a Marine civil engineer asked to do seemingly impossible feats, like building an airfield on frozen ground, and building a bridge in just a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About Douglas MacArthur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was all about him. He loved he vertical pronoun. &amp;quot;I shall return.&amp;quot; The way he used the media, the way he had an entourage everywhere he went, the way he surrounded himself with &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot; men who just told him what he wanted to hear...he had a long, interesting and amazing career, but this was near the very end and I think it had all gone to his head. He just thought he could kick ass and take Korea, and it would be super easy, and didn't think the Chinese would intervene and even if they did it'd be so easy to...you know...and of course he wanted to use nuclear weapons against China when they did intervene, just blow up Beijing no problem. He had by this point become, I think, I very scary dude in the sense of having so much power in this one guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacArthur was not on the ground in Korea. He would fly over occasionally for a photo op.... It's said that he never slept a single night on Korean soil. He's the classic example of an absentee commander. He just was out of touch with reality, and that's where a lot of the problems lie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one the greatest military intelligence failures in our history, and ultimately it's MacArthur's fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happened because diplomacy failed,...because we didn't do the hard, messy work of diplomacy. We didn't have a relationship with the most populace nation on Earth. We refused to recognize Mao as the legitimate leader of China, we had no back channels of communication. He sent ample signals to us that he was going to intervene and we just kind of ignored those signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think of the legacy of this battle as being, exhibit A, what happens when diplomacy fails. And, the other legacy that I really look at here is just how important it is to listen to your field commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole thing could have been avoided if we had listened to what General Smith had to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hamptonsides.com/"&gt;Hampton Sides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Desperate-Ground-Marines-Reservoir-Greatest/dp/0385541155"&gt;On Desperate Ground: The Marines at The Reservoir, the Korean War's Greatest Battle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_P._Smith"&gt;Oliver P. Smith - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_MacArthur"&gt;Douglas MacArthur - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="developer-tea-20190524-crafting-your-work-by-your-strengths"&gt;Developer Tea 20190524 - Crafting Your Work By Your Strengths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/298944"&gt;https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/298944&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-05-26 11:08&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development Field Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map your skill/knowledge strengths/weaknesses to the job's required core/ancillary skills/knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve your weaknesses that are in the job's core.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve your strengths that are in the job's core.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't &lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/browse/deprecate"&gt;deprecate&lt;/a&gt; yourself for weaknesses and mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always look forward to Jonathan's podcast, and rarely find myself critical, but I found this episode unclear and unfocused. I'd like to help clarify what I think Jonathan wanted to promote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As developers, workers, and people, we're faced with deciding whether to improve our weaknesses or our strengths, and which ones. We &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to do both. Focusing on only one or the other is unlikely to lead to success. There's science supporting that only repeating what you're good at doesn't lead to improvement. However, only working on what you're not good at leads to atrophy of your strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a martial artist. If my left side kicks aren't as good as my right side kicks, then I need to work harder at my left ones. There's an implicit goal of parity. However, we sometimes forget (as students and teachers) that the purpose of that goal is improvement, not achievement. It's OK if my left side kicks are never as good as my right ones. It's also OK if I work hard to make my right kicks amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But--to continue the analogy--should I focus on being able to side kick to someone's head who is over six feet tall &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; hold that kick in place? Some kata competition champions can do this. It's their strength. It's not mine. The short answer is &amp;quot;no,&amp;quot; because &lt;em&gt;this is important in the context of competition, but not in my interest which is daily health and self-defense.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that context, let's go back to the podcast and pull the benefit from it. What's a way to help clarify which job skills we should improve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create two lists. One is your skill/knowledge strengths and weaknesses. The other is the job's required core and ancillary skills/knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skill/Knowledge Lists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;( * &lt;em&gt;Starred items are ones I'm naturally good at.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ME&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;JOB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tenacity*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;System Organization*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Customer requirements gathering&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Understanding Customers' Needs*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;REST-ful APIs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Scalable architecture&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WebAPI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Documentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weak&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancillary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Self-confidence&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Employee management&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proven scalability experience&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Documentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Python&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To meet the job's needs, we should always work on the core skills. Give these lists, here's what I'd recommend the fictitious developer focus on improving:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C#, keep improving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer needs, leverage your strength into becoming an expert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebApi, keep improving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalable architecture, work hard at improving this weakness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don't spend much time on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System organization, Tenacity, or Documentation, you're already good enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personnel management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really think this is the essence of what Jonathan was trying to say, but--unusually--the message got lost on a first listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a link from the show notes for a free eBook: &lt;a href="https://resources.gitprime.com/books/20-patterns/?utm_source=podcast&amp;amp;utm_medium=podcast&amp;amp;utm_campaign=podcast"&gt;GitPrime.com/20Patterns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of this episode is to encourage focusing on strengths rather than weaknesses. (No, that's not quite right.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;If you focus on everything you're weak at, it will take a very large jump to go from being weak to strong.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investing time in what your good at takes you from good to great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investing time in what you're not good at takes you from poor to good, but probably not further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One skill may support another skill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working on a weakness may &amp;quot;unlock&amp;quot; a strength.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the core vs ancillary skills needed for the job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform ancillary tasks acceptably, perform core tasks excellently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; strengths to the required core skills. Is there a big mismatch? You either improve those skills, or consider a career change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focusing on ancillary skills isn't as important as focusing on core skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's OK to delegate or collaborate on ancillary skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Job crafting: Look at the skill map, what you're already good at, and &amp;quot;wrap&amp;quot; your job around those skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Cutrell pronounces &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/browse/ancillary"&gt;ancillary&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; the British way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's not saying &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; focus on strengths. I'll call this great quote out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take away the message that you should stop focusing on your weaknesses and only focus on your strengths, &lt;em&gt;it's very possible that you will lose your job&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another message in this episode is it's OK to fail, to learn, as well as not neglect your strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you listen to a lot of podcasts...you may think there's a lot of room for improvement...that there's just this endless hill in front of you. And you may think you have to break yourself down to become the engineer that you want to become. And in many ways, this is true. We all have a lot to learn, and we all have shortcomings.... In today's episode...I want to help you focus on something a little bit different. Rather than looking at self-improvement as a long and arduous task where you are faced with your weaknesses every single day, I want to help you shift to a different point of focus.... If we focus only our shortcomings and weaknesses, we'll likely miss out on major opportunities.... An unintended effet of this show may be that you have taken the time and the energy to beat yourself up when you're not focusing, or to feel bad when you think you haven't broken things down, when you think you've made an assumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these ideas presented on Developer Tea,.. business management/process books, books about software development--all of these things are not intended to fix all your broken parts. Instead, they are intended to be building blocks, foundational, to help push you up rather than break you down. This kind of different way of thinking about your skillset requires a fundamental shift in focus away from your weaknesses and toward your strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you become incredibly good at your ancillary skills then you don't have time to invest in your core skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hanselminutes-685-solving-real-problems-with-software-and-the-human-utility-with-tiffani-ashley-bell"&gt;Hanselminutes #685 - Solving real problems with software and the Human Utility with Tiffani Ashley Bell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hanselminutes.com/685/solving-real-problems-with-software-and-the-human-utility-with-tiffani-ashley-bell"&gt;https://hanselminutes.com/685/solving-real-problems-with-software-and-the-human-utility-with-tiffani-ashley-bell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019-05-26 13:20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developer Field Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an inspiring episode!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are opportunities to improve local government using fairly simple technologies that the employees won't be aware of, or afraid to take a risk on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developers are paid pretty well, and thus privileged. We are in a position to improve the lives of the less fortunate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people don't set out to have problems. Sometimes &amp;quot;life happens.&amp;quot; They break an ankle, and suddenly can't pay their rent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A software-specific understanding of &amp;quot;life happens&amp;quot; is that we don't intend to write bugs, and we can have bad days. We shouldn't be terribly penalized even if our mistake crashes a system. We should be helped up, not beaten down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any system, ensure it's not being taken disadvantage of through validation. (In the Detroit case, they extensively validated the claims)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has found lots of her opportunities on Twitter (prior to the current political environment's negative unfluence on the platform).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read an article about how 100,000 people in Detroit were going to have to live without running water because their water was being shut down due to non-payment. &amp;quot;I thought it was bad...I thought it was really crappy.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great example of using simple technology, putting up a quick and dirty website in a few hours, then letting people know it's available and seeing if they'll come. For the initial Detroit water project, she and her partner used Google Docs and Forms and some Bootstrap. Over the weekend, the started being contacted by people who wanted to help. They then made improvements to allow donorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that was critical was finding and publishing people's actual stories of why they were behind in payment (see quotes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Scott] When you start poking around in local government, with all due respect to all of our hard-working people in government, the solutions they have and the technologoy they have and the gaps can be filled in by pretty straightforward bits of workflow, not rocket science, we don't need machine learning to make it easier for someone to find out when to come to pay their parking ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get these situations where cities have multi-million dollar contracts to really large corporations that make [for instance] databases, when they could really be using something a lot simpler in a lot of different places, because some salesperson came in, convinced a person who didn't know how to buy these things, or didn't know the he could go somewhere and perhaps download something and still get support.... They're used to these big enterprise companies coming in and offering that, and at great expense. But they don't realize it doesn't take all these heavy solutions to do simple things for citizens, and that lack of knowhow isn't there in a lot of situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think also...people don't want to get in trouble for the things that they buy. What's the old saying? &amp;quot;You never get fired for buying IBM.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Scott] These are folks [Detroit who couldn't pay water bill] who are maybe on disability...one person was written up in National Geographic...who received a $672 monthly check, but her rent was $600, so she had $72 left at the end of the month, and slowly, slowly, slowly...got a $500 overdue water bill, so they came to her house and turned off her water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this happened to tens of thousands of people in Detroit--who had 90 million dollars in bad debt--and shut offs were being called in for anyone who owed $150 or more, and it seems that for some people that's a crushingly huge amount of money, and for other people, like you said, it's a bad meal for four in the Bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the stories I think about was a woman...she had three kids...who skimped on her heart medication, cut her pills in half...to pay the water bill each month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/HumanUtility"&gt;https://twitter.com/HumanUtility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.detroitwaterproject.org"&gt;https://www.detroitwaterproject.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception that Trump appears to have had far fewer successes than he claims.&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 14:14:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/flatts_posts-casts_review_002_-_real_problems__strengths__korean_war</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/flatts_posts-casts_review_002_-_real_problems__strengths__korean_war</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 50-10 Time Box - Revising Pomodoro for Software Development</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/the_50-10_time_box_revising_pomodoro_for_software_development_repost/images/time-box.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a slightly edited repost of an article I wrote last year. I think it's valuable enough to promote the technique again, along with the supporting science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us have trouble with three aspects of programming:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cost of interruptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Methods for staying on task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The benefits of taking breaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these has studies behind it (see References), as well as anecdotal information. The simple question I wanted to answer is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's an effective work-break cycle for programming?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three most common cycles I know of are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pomodoro - 25 minutes work, 5 minutes break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;52/17 - 52 minutes work, 17 minutes break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;90/? - 90 minutes work, then a break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="pomodoro"&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pomodoro Technique is popular, and, besides the work-break cycle, has these suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan the tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check off completed tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record interruptions so you can return to them outside the work interval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, Pomodoro, to my knowledge, hasn't been studied scientifically. When I used it for non-programming tasks, I could see the benefit. The more I tried using it for programming, the less effective I found it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-task-recovery-lag"&gt;The Task Recovery Lag&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies show there's a recovery lag when resuming an interrupted task. For software developers, it takes about fifteen minutes to recover the previous context--to &amp;quot;get back to where I was.&amp;quot; The worst time to be interrupted is when there's the highest mental workload. (Like when I'm in the middle of debugging a method having spent twenty minutes understanding how it relates to five other modules.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's a mistake, though, to think only in terms of interruptions. A programmer &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; ramps up when starting (or restarting) a coding session. In other words, we should plan on the first fifteen minutes being devoted to recovering context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="breaks"&gt;Breaks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've worked for hours straight, and thought I was being productive. Maybe sometimes I was. But the research shows that regular breaks improve productivity, because the brain needs that time to recover from fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-friction"&gt;The Friction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, where does that leave us regarding Pomodoro?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It takes a programmer at least fifteen minutes to &amp;quot;ramp up&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Pomodoro work period is twenty-five minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That leaves &lt;em&gt;ten minutes or less of effective work time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no wonder Pomodoro wasn't working out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried the 52/17 cycle. I found the seventeen minute break too long. I read an article where office workers tried it themselves, and it was pretty challenging. I suspect that the original study wasn't looking at programmers....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are benefits to Pomodoro. The task planning and completion help a lot with emotionally attaching to success, and with chunking down larger items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="proposal-the-50-10-time-box"&gt;Proposal - The 50-10 Time Box&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been trying this for over a year now, and it's working well for me. So, maybe it will work for you, too. Basically, use Pomodoro Technique but with a 50 minute work cycle followed by a ten minute break. This allows for the fifteen minute ramp up, then thirty-five minutes of solid, focused work. I've found that I'm usually ready for a break at the fifty minute mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even if I wasn't &amp;quot;ready&amp;quot; for a break, when I took it I found I needed it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use an online tool named &lt;a href="http://www.marinaratimer.com/"&gt;Marinara Timer&lt;/a&gt; to manage my time boxes. It has a Custom timer where I configured my cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/the_50-10_time_box_revising_pomodoro_for_software_development_repost/images/2018-04-21%2009_04_45.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I like about this approach?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It aligns on the hour, making it easy to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get enough context recovery time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Four cycles gets me to lunch, the remaing four finish my day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A ten minute break is enough to take a walk, catch up on email, even have a short conversation. It's an effective coding break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That break has often helped me solve a thorny problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improves my task estimates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A complete work session looks like this. I use a Markdown document to track my work sessions, distractions and notes, but paper and pen (or pencil!) would work as well or better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Plan my tasks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;# Distractions

# Round 1
- [ ] Validation rules
- [ ] Unit tests

# Round 2
- [ ] Review code, make sure setting values correctly
- [ ] Improve queries based on understanding of rules

# Round 3
- [ ] Design workhorse feature

# Round 4
- [ ] Begin coding workhorse feature
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Start my timer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/the_50-10_time_box_revising_pomodoro_for_software_development_repost/images/2018-04-21%2009_17_06.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Work deliberately, with intense focus. Record distractions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to not noodle around during the work time. Manage distractions! This is a hallmark of &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2007/07/the-making-of-an-expert"&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;, and an aspect of &lt;a href="http://whatmeditationreallyis.com/index.php/home-blog/item/470-how-to-meditate-distraction-in-meditation-doesnt-matter.html"&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; and mindfulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;# Distractions
- [ ] Email from Luis, not urgent but should get back to him soon.
- [ ] Birthday gift research for Joanie.

# Round 1
- [ ] Validation rules
- [ ] Unit tests
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Check off tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;# Distractions
- [ ] Email from Luis, not urgent but should get back to him soon.
- [ ] Birthday gift research for Joanie.

# Round 1
- [x] Validation rules
- [ ] Unit tests
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. When the work cycle ends (I'm currently enamoured of the Whoosh sound), take a break.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be hard to stop, but do it. And, I recommend walking away from the desk, and/or closing your work windows, so you don't get sucked back into the task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Repeat.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was spurred to write this post because of &lt;a href="https://www.7pace.com/blog/time-blocking-for-developers-how-to-achieve-flow-stop-being-busy-start-being-productive"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. The author, Tyler Hakes, gives several examples from his workday of how he reduces interruptions in his day, and it's worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are a bunch of references I read both before and while creating this entry. They include links to the primary research papers that other articles refer to. I've called out some quotes that I found useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.7pace.com/blog/time-blocking-for-developers-how-to-achieve-flow-stop-being-busy-start-being-productive"&gt;Time Blocking for Developers: How to Achieve Flow, Stop Being “Busy”, &amp;amp; Start Being Productive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Programmer Interrupted](Programmer Interrupted) &amp;lt;= A key article by a researcher whose study is often cited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/944128/worker-interrupted-cost-task-switching"&gt;Worker, Interrupted: The Cost of Task Switching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://lifehacker.com/how-long-it-takes-to-get-back-on-track-after-a-distract-1720708353"&gt;How Long It Takes to Get Back on Track After a Distraction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://daedtech.com/programmers-teach-non-geeks-the-true-cost-of-interruptions/"&gt;Programmers, Teach Non-Geeks The True Cost of Interruptions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ironistic.com/the-cost-of-distractions-on-developers/"&gt;The Cost of Distractions on Developers!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/noodleeducation/2016/04/26/the-pomodoro-technique-and-3-more-research-backed-study-tips/#520044465027"&gt;The Pomodoro Technique And 3 More Research-Backed Study Tips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.themuse.com/advice/the-rule-of-52-and-17-its-random-but-it-ups-your-productivity"&gt;How the Most Productive People Schedule Their Day - The Rule of 52 and 17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/tony-schwartz/work-life-balance-the-90_b_578671.html"&gt;The 90-Minute Solution: How Building in Periods of Renewal Can Change Your Work and Your Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/12/19/youve-been-taking-breaks-_n_4453448.html"&gt;ou’ve Been Taking Breaks All Wrong. Here’s How To Do It Right.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/kate-bartolotta/5-science-backed-ways-taking-a-break-boosts-our-productivity_b_8548292.html"&gt;5 Science-Backed Ways Taking a Break Boosts Our Productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique"&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="papers"&gt;Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://chrisparnin.me/pdf/parnin-icpc09.pdf"&gt;Resumption Strategies for Interrupted Programming Tasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When resuming an incomplete programming task, the developer must remember their previous working state and recover knowledge about the software. Details of working state might include recalling plans, intentions, and goals. Details of knowledge might include plan progress, component mechanisms, and domain representations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/%7Egmark/chi08-mark.pdf"&gt;The Cost of Interrupted Work: More Speed and Stress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our data suggests that people compensate for interruptions by working faster, but this comes at a price: experiencing more stress, higher frustration, time pressure and effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://erichorvitz.com/CHI_2007_Iqbal_Horvitz.pdf"&gt;Disruption and Recovery of Computing Tasks:  Field Study, Analysis, and Directions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/220093595_Interrupts_Just_a_Minute_Never_Is"&gt;Just a minute never is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DeMarco reports that the recovery time after a phone call is at least 15 minutes.2 Even though we could not measure recovery time exactly, we believe his estimate to be valid. If more than 10 interrupts occur during a day, the time between the interrupts becomes too short to accomplish product development work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://users.dcc.uchile.cl/%7Errobbes/p/SANER15-fragmentation.pdf"&gt;An Empirical Study of Work Fragmentation in Software Evolution Tasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work fragmentation as result of interruptions usually demands extra effort to recover and resume pending activities: a study of 24 information workers found that a worker needs on average 25 minutes to get back on an interrupted task [5]. Similarly, Iqbal and Horvitz [6] found that people experience disorientation and loss of context when multitasking. Czerwinsky et al. found that after experiencing work fragmentation people found it more difficult to perform interrupted tasks and took longer to complete them [7].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://interruptions.net/literature/Iqbal-CHI05-p1489-iqbal.pdf"&gt;Investigating the Effectiveness of Mental Workload as a Predictor of Opportune Moments for Interruption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 23:08:12 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/the_50-10_time_box_revising_pomodoro_for_software_development_repost</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/the_50-10_time_box_revising_pomodoro_for_software_development_repost</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>