<?xml version="1.0" encoding ="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Meadows</title>
    <description>A pleasant walk through computing</description>
    <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/feed</link>
    <link href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" />
    <item>
      <title>My Mixed Relationship with TDD</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/my_mixed_relationship_with_tdd/images/tdd-created-by-nasa.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;OK, not completely &amp;quot;created by,&amp;quot; but &lt;a href="https://arialdomartini.wordpress.com/2012/07/20/you-wont-believe-how-old-tdd-is/"&gt;You won't believe how old TDD is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="intro"&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a mixed relationship with Test-Driven Development (TDD). It's a valuable method that I've enjoyed--when I've used it. What matters more to me than test-first is creating automated tests early rather than late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my on-again, off-again history with TDD, I've written about it in tutorial form. This series also includes examples of mocking and dependency injection. What to mock is, I think, especially difficult to get right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/catching-up-on-coding-tdd-part-1/"&gt;Catching Up On Coding - TDD Part 1 | Software Meadows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/catching-up-on-coding-tdd-part-2/"&gt;Catching Up On Coding - TDD Part 2 | Software Meadows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/catching-up-on-coding-tdd-part-3/"&gt;Catching Up On Coding - TDD Part 3 | Software Meadows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="history"&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2001, at the beginning of the third millenium, I first learned about some eXtreme Programming (XP) practices, among them TDD. I wanted to try this out, but ran into a snag: Visual Basic 6 didn't have a good unit testing framework. &lt;a id="fnref:1" href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So, I wrote my own. I also wrote it to test &lt;em&gt;private&lt;/em&gt; methods, because that's where the action was, and I hadn't yet wrapped my head around why testing public methods was key to keeping tests separate from code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even then, I got the TDDers thrill from seeing all green after running tests. However, my organization wasn't invested in TDD, so I set it aside. This was the story for the next couple of decades. The places I worked didn't care about more agile methods, and my efforts to introduce and use TDD didn't go far. Over time, I realized something else. My background in creative writing and music composition led me intuitively write code in a particular way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draft the code, getting some things working quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significantly rewrite as the better structure reveals itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD didn't fit into this way of coding new projects, because my code would often change a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; as I settled on the most effective patterns. In business parlance, this is a &amp;quot;fail early, fail often&amp;quot; approach. Writing tests first at this stage worked against me because the methods I was testing were in flux. Heck, the whole approach was in flux. I could delete them at any moment. It took me a long time to reconcile how to integrate unit testing and TDD into my personal, fluid--and effective--style of coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One developer I talked with said his team didn't practice &amp;quot;test first,&amp;quot; but instead &amp;quot;test eventually.&amp;quot; I stored this tidbit away, though something nagged at me. How often was &amp;quot;test eventually&amp;quot; turning into &amp;quot;test never?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="database-testing"&gt;Database Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another obstacle on my road to successful unit testing was how to deal with databases. This wasn't just my obstacle, of course. It hung up loads of developers. The Repository Pattern was known, but not well-understood or encouraged in the Microsoft world. Abstracting the database seemed--and often was--tedious, time-consuming, and prohibitively maintenance-heavy. What kind of software was I writing all the time? Yep, database-centric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things didn't because easier with the adoption of Entity Framework (or Linq2Sql). When it came to testing, Microsoft's own documentation often recommended Repository Pattern, and sometimes Unit of Work.&lt;a id="fnref:2" href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This was frankly a mess. Why? Because EF was itself built using Repository (DbSet) and Unit of Work (DbContext) patterns.&lt;a id="fnref:3" href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So, developers were writing &lt;em&gt;an abstraction on top of an abstraction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I was hampered by a couple of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a regular employee, I wasn't working in an agile environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a contractor, I was often constrained by client expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="today"&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I've returned to TDD several times and have come to some tentative conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For me, on a greenfield project, test-first shouldn't be introduced immediately, but only after going through my drafting/iterating process to help clarify how &amp;quot;the code wants to be written&amp;quot; (I agree, a squishy, woo-woo statement.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After that, TDD is a big help, primarily because it forces tests to be written in parallel to coding &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; forces useful abstractions and separation of concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes, though, TDD needs to be set aside while a coding solution is explored via a deep dive. Avoid &lt;em&gt;premature testing&lt;/em&gt;. In these cases, the developer's mind needs to &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Testing reveals architecture problems&lt;/em&gt;. This is another top value. In order for code to be testable, it needs to be well-architected using dependency injection and coding to interfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm insisting on unit tests in my code, and forcing myself to use TDD in my workflow. This will require reading about modern TDD, and being confronted with terrific articles such as &lt;a href="http://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2017/03/03/TDD-Harms-Architecture.html"&gt;TDD Harms Architecture&lt;/a&gt; by &amp;quot;Uncle Bob&amp;quot; Martin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="other-thoughts"&gt;Other Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="not-design"&gt;Not &amp;quot;Design&amp;quot;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; design. Some people want the acronym to be Test Driven Design. But TDD isn't designing anything, except in the very loosest sense that programmers are always designing a method before coding it. We at least &lt;em&gt;imagine&lt;/em&gt; how it's going to work, and that's--again, loosely--design. Robert Martin says it emphatically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that the high level design and architecture of a system emerge from TDD is, frankly, absurd. Before you begin to code any software project, you need to have some architectural vision in place. TDD will not, and can not, provide this vision. That is not TDD’s role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And goes on to say&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this does not mean that designs do not emerge from TDD – they do; just not at the highest levels. The designs that emerge from TDD are one or two steps above the code;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="favorite-framework"&gt;Favorite Framework&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's easy. &lt;a href="https://xunit.net/"&gt;xUnit.net&lt;/a&gt;. I've loved it since its early days. Now, I've often used MSTest because it's A) built-in, and/or B) it's what the development shop was already using. But I prefer xUnit.net and its features such as Theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using one of the &amp;quot;Should&amp;quot;&lt;a id="fnref:4" href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; libraries makes unit testing even more readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrap-up"&gt;Wrap-Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing is hard. Unit testing is hard. But early, automated testing builds confidence in the system, and TDD provides a valuable feedback loop that stacks nicely on other methods such as continuous integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't quite true. There was a framework, but my misunderstanding of why only public methods should be tested interfered with me using it.&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such as this untestable craziness: &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/mvc/overview/older-versions/getting-started-with-ef-5-using-mvc-4/implementing-the-repository-and-unit-of-work-patterns-in-an-asp-net-mvc-application"&gt;Implementing the Repository and Unit of Work Patterns in an ASP.NET MVC Application (9 of 10) | Microsoft Docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not until EF 4.1, and mocking wasn't easy-ish until 6.0.&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/shouldly/shouldly"&gt;shouldly&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://fluentassertions.com/"&gt;Fluent Assertions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 09:24:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/my_mixed_relationship_with_tdd</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/my_mixed_relationship_with_tdd</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Be a Lazy Programmer Like Matthew Jones Isn't</title>
      <description>&lt;img src="https://larrycuban.files.wordpress.com/2015/11/4505206e894208cab03f96c4703cac93.gif"  width=500 /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#examination"&gt;Examination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#refutation"&gt;Refutation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#is-laziness-bad"&gt;Is Laziness Bad?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#then-what-is-matthew-jones"&gt;Then What is Matthew Jones?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew Jones recently wrote a blog article titled &lt;a href="https://exceptionnotfound.net/be-the-laziest-programmer-you-can-be/"&gt;Be The Laziest Programmer You Can Be&lt;/a&gt;. I like Matthew's articles, and I like this one in a way, but I'm going to make a case that Matthew's &lt;em&gt;completely wrong in his definition of lazy&lt;/em&gt;. This is one of those subjects that rankles me, kind of like computer people routinely misusing the word &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/browse/deprecate?s=t"&gt;deprecate&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional statemnent of Matthew's gist is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to find the most efficient way to do a job, give it to a lazy person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew states his thesis as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lazy programmers want to do as little work as possible right now.  But they also want to do as little &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt; work as possible,...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's absolutely right about the first part, doing as little work as possible right now. But he's absolutely wrong about the second, that lazy programmers are concerned about the future. They aren't, that's the problem. And, they're not efficient, they just get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examination"&gt;Examination&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's hit the &lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/browse/lazy?s=t"&gt;dictionary&lt;/a&gt; first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;adjective&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;la·zi·er, la·zi·est.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;averse or disinclined to work, activity, or exertion; indolent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;causing idleness or indolence:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a hot, lazy afternoon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow-moving; sluggish:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a lazy stream&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(of a livestock brand) placed on its side instead of upright.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;verb (used without object)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;la·zied, la·zy·ing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
5. to laze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Averse or disinclined to work.&amp;quot; This isn't decisive, because one could argue--as Matthew does--that a disincilation to work could extend toward future work. What does science have to say?  [Emphases mine]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person is being lazy if he is able to carry out some activity that he ought to carry out, but is disinclined to do so because of the effort involved. Instead, he carries out the activity perfunctorily; or engages in some other, less strenuous or less boring activity; or remains idle. In short, &lt;em&gt;he is being lazy if his motivation to spare himself effort trumps his motivation to do the right or expected thing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/hide-and-seek/201410/the-psychology-laziness"&gt;The Psychology of Laziness | Psychology Today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other aspects of laziness that are discussed in a brief review of the psychology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Procrastination&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Laziness and procrastination are similar in that they both involve a lack of motivation. But, &lt;em&gt;unlike a lazy person, a procrastinator aspires and intends to complete the task&lt;/em&gt; and, moreover, does eventually complete it, albeit at a higher cost to himself.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolution&lt;/strong&gt;  Our nomadic ancestors had to conserve energy to compete for scarce resources and to fight or flee enemies and predators. Expending effort on anything other than short-term advantage could jeopardize their very survival.... &lt;em&gt;it made little sense to think long term&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effort and Reward&lt;/strong&gt;  &amp;quot;In most cases, it is deemed painful to expend effort on long-term goals that do not provide immediate gratification. For a person to embark on a project, he has to value the return on his labour more than his loss of comfort. &lt;em&gt;The problem is that he is disinclined to trust in a return that is both distant and uncertain&lt;/em&gt;. Because self-confident people are more apt to trust in the success and pay-off of their undertakings (and may even overestimate their likely returns), they are much more likely to overcome their natural laziness.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, from &lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/contemporary-psychoanalysis-in-action/201510/7-reasons-why-laziness-is-myth"&gt;7 Reasons Why Laziness Is a Myth | Psychology Today&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of failure.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Many people get in their own way by postponing the pursuit of goals,&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of success.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;This cousin of the fear of failure is very real: Many people are unconsciously worried that they’ll succeed in ways potentially threatening to others. So they avoid conflict by not moving forward.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desire for nuture.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;some of us don’t know how to ask for what we want directly—so we act useless as a way of getting others to do things for us.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of expectations.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;One of my patients rarely made plans and established herself as “lazy” so that other people would plan for her.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passive-aggresive communication.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;People who avoid conflict often bury their dissatisfied feelings. They may communicate them indirectly through “laziness,” slacking in a way that will upset another person.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need for relaxation.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Many people erroneously assume that they should always be going full steam, and chastise themselves for being “lazy” when their body and mind shut down in protest.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depression.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;In criticizing himself for “laziness,” a man may miss signs that he is depressed and needs treatment.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This picture of laziness is much clearer. According to established social and science understandings, a lazy person:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoids doing hard work now, and so does the easiest thing he can get away with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isn't influenced by (or concerned with) future consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some attributes of a lazy developer&lt;a id="fnref:1" href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doesn't write thorough unit tests. Tests, if written, allow him to fit the requirement, but don't catch enough problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doesn't use consistent naming conventions. He uses whatever occurs to him at the moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only updates Scrum/project estimates and completions if pushed to do so, and probably days after the fact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes no or cursory source control comments upon commit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source code only works on his machine, unless he's been forced otherwise through continuous integration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="refutation"&gt;Refutation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is Matthew a &amp;quot;lazy&amp;quot; programmer? No, of course, not, but now I'm in for a pound so let's go through his article point-by-point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;why don't I hear you typing?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Matthew got in trouble for being lazy for not typing enough. This was a management failure, pure and simple. And it's proven by the company having an overtime-oriented culture. I'll bet &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; were lazy because they weren't planning ahead, as Matthew was. That guy was wrong and a jerk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lazy programmers are &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; programmers.  They don't do more work than absolutely necessary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. The confusion here is in the word &amp;quot;necessary.&amp;quot; For Matthew, &amp;quot;necessary&amp;quot; means &amp;quot;do it right so we reduce doing it again.&amp;quot; Lazy programmers define &amp;quot;necessary&amp;quot; as &amp;quot;required by something external.&amp;quot; Let me call this one out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refactoring doesn't exist for the lazy programmer. It's not in his vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lazy programmers abhor redundancy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just the opposite. A lazy programmer will copy/paste code all day, because he's a) finishing more work &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;, and b) doesn't expect to have to fix the code later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lazy programmers explain their decisions.  They write thorough comments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope. Lazy programmers, concerned only with the present, see explanations as a waste of time. &amp;quot;Working&amp;quot; code should be good enough, they reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lazy programmer is not attached to his future self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lazy programmers automate everything that can possibly be automated&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would take foresight. I've seen this repeatedly, programmers who are too lazy to encapsulate a method, or write a utility to automate. They'll instead do it the long, hard way every time. Their justification? &amp;quot;Writing that utility will take too long!&amp;quot; (This thinking is further exacerbated by deadline-oriented management.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lazy programmers teach people more junior than them, partially so those junior people can do the work instead.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of this is right. Lazy programmers want to get other people doing their work. But the way they do it is to claim they're too busy to fix their own code, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; too busy to explain clearly, so &lt;em&gt;just figure it out.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lazy programmers expect to be replaced.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; expect this, but are not only surprised when it happens, but also angry, because they think they're doing what was expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be lazy. It's OK.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it isn't, because you're not. Programmers!, don't conflate laziness with other problems. And don't beat yourselves up, either! Get help with beliefs and root causes. Learn to value strategic thinking, to give yourself a positive boost about creating that automation utility. To see your future self grinning like mad and saying &amp;quot;This used to take the other guy four hours. I automated it and it's done in four minutes.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It [laziness] takes practice,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be pretty clear by now, but lazy people don't practice. I play violin. I'm prety good. But one reason I don't play violin really, really well is because I only practiced enough to get by. (I also didn't know about &lt;a href="https://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice-theory"&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;, but that's another story.) A lazy person, by definition, avoids effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellence requires continual effort&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="is-laziness-bad"&gt;Is Laziness Bad?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. Well, maybe. The behavior's not helpful, and often harmful. The thing is, lazy &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; aren't bad. It's &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a disease, and it's &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a character or moral defect. As noted above, there are people who get huge amounts done, but if they rest they demean themselves as lazy. That's unhealthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laziness is a habit. And &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Atomic-Habits-Proven-Build-Break/dp/0735211299/ref=sr_1_2?keywords=atomic+habits&amp;amp;qid=1555604333&amp;amp;s=gateway&amp;amp;sr=8-2"&gt;habits can be broken&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="then-what-is-matthew-jones"&gt;Then What is Matthew Jones?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's pretty easy. Matthew is an &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;effective developer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. All of the positive traits he ascribes to laziness are in fact hallmarks of high-performing software engineers. Matthew:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is concerned with how his current actions impact his future self.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is likewise concerned with making his code easier for other developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plans. Then executes. Then &lt;em&gt;reviews and improves&lt;/em&gt;. He practices &lt;em&gt;kaizen&lt;/em&gt;. He refactors mercilessly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coaches others and, I hope, is always willing to be confronted with opposition, otherwise I probably wouldn't have taken the time to write all this down. Because, Matthew...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is wrong about what it means to be a lazy programmer, and I hope he revises his pitch. It's great to help programmers not be lazy, but I don't think redefining a word to mean its opposite is a good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew, I have a feeling I'd like you if we sat down for a beer. If you're ever in Denver, let's find out. You take your craft seriously, and have a light-hearted writing voice. It's from that mindset that I'm telling you, firmly, kindly: Matthew, buddy, you are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a lazy programmer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry that these are all in the masculine. Unfortunately, 90% of programmers are guys, so I'm writing to the majority audience.&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-back-ref"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 09:01:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/dont_be_a_lazy_programmer_like_matthew_jones_isnt</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/dont_be_a_lazy_programmer_like_matthew_jones_isnt</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personal Reflections on Removing Distractions for Improved Productivity</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/personal_reflections_on_removing_distractions_for_improved_productivity/images/reflection.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a couple of experiments with reducing distractions
(&lt;a href="https://www.flattland.com/posts/month_of_mu_week_1/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_week_of_web_blocking_for_productivity_and_well-being/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Since then, I've taken the weed-whacker to Facebook, only check the news a couple of times a day, and (try to) restrict my Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for me professionally and personally?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="facebook"&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I don't miss Facebook one bit. The research is pretty clear that social media &lt;a href="(https://hbr.org/2017/04/a-new-more-rigorous-study-confirms-the-more-you-use-facebook-the-worse-you-feel)"&gt;makes us unhappy&lt;/a&gt;. What alarms me in retrospect is that Facebook use seems like an addiction: something bad for you, but you can't stop doing. Consider these stats from a recent &lt;a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/meet-the-press/poll-americans-give-social-media-clear-thumbs-down-n991086"&gt;NBC News/Wall Street Journal poll&lt;/a&gt; on social media usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;69% of adults in the US said &amp;quot;they use such services at least once a day.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And yet, &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;82% of Americans believe social media is a waste of time.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;57% said social media &amp;quot;does more to divide us.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;55% said &amp;quot;social media does more to spread lies and falsehoods.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been pretty careful for a long time about what services I sign up for. I can't deny the influence of Twitter, but I never understood the appeal of reading people's mundane, off-the-cuff thoughts, or publishing my own. I never signed up. Likewise, no SnapChat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I only had Facebook to deal with. I was a little worried about losing contact with my FB friends, but realized a) I only had about thirty FB friends, and b) that worry was a &lt;em&gt;symptom of the FB disease&lt;/em&gt;. The solution was easy, I asked all my FB friends via instant messenger if they'd give me their email addresses so I could stay in touch. Many did. Anxiety-crisis averted. I backed up and deleted my account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What now? That's easy, too. How about I make more &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;, in-person friends? You know, the kind that research shows actually increase well-being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news is inherently depressing, and apparently &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20140728-why-is-all-the-news-bad"&gt;we love it&lt;/a&gt;. Even as a kid (back in the three-network days), I hated watching or listening to the TV news because it sounded ugly. This doesn't mean news isn't important. A free, independent press is critical to democracy, and those who vilify it while getting all their &amp;quot;news&amp;quot; from talk radio are, frankly, ignorant and deluded. But there's only so much reporting of the current socio-political awfulness a person should read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used a browser blocker to keep me from reading the news during the day for several weeks. I'm pretty good now at only dipping into Google News and NPR a couple of times a day. I know from past experience I can go weeks at a time without checking the news because if something really, really important happens I'm sure I'll hear about it. Here's the way I now see being a news junkie:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news is like Facebook. Emotionally, it's more like gossip, and is addictive in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact is, I can't do much, if anything, about what's in the news. So why obsess and clamor and complain over what I can't change, when I can fill my life with plenty that I can?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="netflix-et-al"&gt;Netflix, et al&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my bane. Netflix, Amazon Prime Video, CWTV, IMDb FreeDive, YouTube...I'm still addicted to streaming media. It's not wrong for me to enjoy a little TV and movies, but it's too often a go-to break from work or other activities. Is this bad? Yep, for the same reasons as above. It keeps me away from real, live social interactions. There's also evidence that watching TV has negative mental effects, while reading has positive effects. (Sorry, I don't have a link to this right now.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current solution to this is strict time-blocking. I try to only watch Netflix during certain times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know when I'm watching too much TV. I can feel it, and that's compounded by my profession as a software engineer. My job is at the computer, so all together I can end up spending sixteen hours a day on the thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="meditation-woop-time-boxing-habits-whew"&gt;Meditation, WOOP, Time-Boxing, Habits: Whew!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removing distractions has helped my productivity and well-being. But it's not enough. To create a healthier work balance, I needed to retrain my brain. Fortunately, we live in a great time for research into well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Proper meditation, where the wandering mind (the Default Mental Network) is stilled, helps not only with mental/emotional health but also distraction. After all, the wandering mind &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; distraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WOOP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is a great technique for establishing new behaviors and habits. It can be done daily in a few minutes. I've used this to manage overwhelm when facing a large task list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify what you &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt;ish for (the goal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagine and emotionally invest in the &lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;utcome(s). It's valuable to imagine the affect on the future self.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagine and emotionally invest in the &lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;bstacle(s). Again, what's the affect on the future self?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a simple If-Then &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;lan. &amp;quot;When this happens, I will do this.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Do not &amp;quot;flip the Os&amp;quot;. Imagine outcomes first, then obstacles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time-Boxing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I've adopted a 50-10 time box. &lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/the_50-10_time_box_revising_pomodoro_for_software_development/"&gt;Read my blog article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Habits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are great books on how to break and make habits, based on science. For those who love podcasts, here's an &lt;a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/building-breaking-habits/"&gt;interview with the author of Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="final-reflections"&gt;Final Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had to overcome some challenges in the past couple of years. Thankfully, I have a wife who loves me, and my clients have been happy with my work. I enjoy reading about science and well-being, and enjoy even more &lt;em&gt;applying&lt;/em&gt; what I learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, my experiments have been a success.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 9 Apr 2019 09:24:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/personal_reflections_on_removing_distractions_for_improved_productivity</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/personal_reflections_on_removing_distractions_for_improved_productivity</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creating a Modern, Practical Résumé</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/creating_a_modern__practical_resume/images/resume.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently asked to review a résumé, which gave me a chance to think about the purpose and use of résumés today versus decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear from the start: I'm not an HR professional, so I'm offering only a view of a slice of hiring. Still, as an &amp;quot;old man,&amp;quot; I'm fascinated by how such a simple item has changed. Here's most of what I wrote as advice to the person who asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the purpose of a résumé has changed over the last couple of decades. It used to be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; introduction of a person to an organization. But this is far less true today. When applying for a job, you'll be asked to upload your résumé, or enter the information into an online form. Your employment and education will probably be verified by a third party. A résumé is still, though, a useful way to document and present your qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your résumé is a way to learn about yourself. It's for &lt;strong&gt;discovery&lt;/strong&gt; as well as presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at résumés in terms of these desired outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything about the résumé makes it easy for employers to find what they need to know&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to contact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education and employment histories are clear and verifiable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relevant skills receive focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be easily imported into a database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="structure"&gt;Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't get caught up in formatting at first, it'll just distract from the content. As noted elsewhere, the primary concern for formatting is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; how the résumé looks, but how easy it is to convert to electronic data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a throw-away draft where you really focus on information and not style. I suggest using a plain-text editor such as Microsoft Notepad with these sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Contact Information

Professional Mission

Skills

Experience

Education
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within these, just fill in all the info. Figure out how to style the document later. In fact, your résumé should be perfectly readable in plain text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contact-information"&gt;Contact Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep all contact information together, in a simple format such as this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Email
Phone
Address
[Your web site]
[LinkedIn profile]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you include your (professional) web site, be sure it's what you want an employer to see. If you include LinkedIn, make sure that profile is up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="professional-mission"&gt;Professional Mission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a key discovery area. What you write here probably won't make it into your résumé directly, but it will influence what you include, how you write your cover letters, where you apply, and how you present yourself at an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't what job you want in the near term, but what your larger desires are. What matters to you? What kind of person do you imagine being in five years? Twenty years? What kind of organization do you want to end up in? What kind of culture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can easily spend hours—heck, years—on this, and it'll change over time. Once you've taken a deep dive, summarize your professional mission as &amp;quot;what&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;when.&amp;quot; For example, &amp;quot;Within five years, I want to be teaching national courses on academic preparation and success.&amp;quot; The more specific, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what do you include on the résumé? Arguably, nothing. The potential employer assumes you're interested in the position you've applied for. Don't include an Objective for the sake of it. Still, including a brief statement can be valuable. If you do, make it a &lt;em&gt;summary of you&lt;/em&gt;. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Experienced college-level tutor in English and Creative Writing, dedicated to helping high school and college students succeed in their learning objectives.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id="skills"&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of your skills more specifically in terms of the job(s) you're applying for. You may be tweaking the Skills section depending on the job requirements. Be specific, brief, and use industry language. This area should honestly match up with the job description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Skills

* Strong interpersonal techniques, including open-ended questions, 
  active listening.
* Apply various learning theories: VARK model, Transfer, Gestalt
* Create subject-specific and student-specific study guides
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast this to the skills you'd highlight if you were applying to an education tech writing job. They'd be different. So, &lt;em&gt;yes, you may be creating different résumés for different places&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure that whatever your write here, you're telling the truth. In an interview, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be asked about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, the VARK learning model is baloney. Don't use it. &lt;a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/04/the-myth-of-learning-styles/557687/"&gt;The Myth of Learning Styles - Atlantic Monthly&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="experience"&gt;Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All experience should be verifiable. That means someone can be called. So, make it easy for the verifier. Include the organization or individual's phone number. Experience should &lt;em&gt;start with the most recent&lt;/em&gt;, and include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From – To using month and year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phone Number&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What you did&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Experience

Colorado State University-Pueblo
123-555-1234
4/2017 – 7/2017

*   Organized and ran weekly tutoring sessions for fellow students
*   Created and distributed. . . .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful of being wordy. Don't pad. Be concrete and specific. Think of the person reading the résumé: she just wants the facts to decide whether to interview you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="education"&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't need to include a phone number, but do use a &amp;quot;most to least&amp;quot; format. School &amp;gt; Degree &amp;gt; Graduation Date&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Education

University of Colorado Denver
Bachelor of Arts in English Literature, 9/2018
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id="formatting"&gt;Formatting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where people used to really differentiate, and still try to. They get hung up on how the résumé looks, what paper they use, etc. What's important is clarity and—in my opinion—the ability to import. Manually styling makes it hard to do the latter. To make it easy for the machine, use consistent header styles. Styles also let you easily change the look of your résumé.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't know how to work with styles in your word processer, look it up! Here's an &lt;a href="https://business.tutsplus.com/tutorials/how-to-simplify-word-document-formatting-with-styles--cms-21069"&gt;article to get you started&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At minimum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give each section (contact, skills, etc) a Heading 2 styles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put school/business names on separate lines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Format dates consistently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use bullet points consistently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the above, be judicious and consistent with how you use bold weight. Are you drawing attention to what matters? (And remember online submission probably won't allow bold, italic, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about this, too: when you need to copy/paste information into an online form, how easy will it be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not finding a service that lets you check if your résumé is easily parse-able, but you'll know as soon as you apply somewhere that lets you upload your résumé.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="other"&gt;Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked for a background check company for several years, so my advice is based on that experience. HR departments outsource their verifications and use third party software to import all résumé information into a database. They don't keep file folders of applications and résumés.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you check online, you'll find businesses that can produce beautiful résumés. But why bother? Employers are looking at your data. Make it easy to get them that data. (You should still have a nice-looking résumé, though.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what's a person to do when looking for a job and building a career? I'm certainly no expert, but here's what I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn what your strengths are, what you love to do, and find work that lets you do that. The science of well-being shows the job won't make you happy. Using your strengths will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Target the places you want to be. Research them. Make it clear to yourself that you don't just want a job, you want to work &lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk into an interview prepared to start working immediately. You won't be asked to do that, but it'll affect how you dress and behave.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take two or more copies of your résumé with you. One for you, one for the interviewer if she doesn't have one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be prepared to ask questions. Take notes during the interview. Your goal is the same as theirs. Do you want to work here?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, I think fundamentally a good organization cares about these questions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can&lt;/strong&gt; the person do the job&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will&lt;/strong&gt; the person do the job&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the person &lt;strong&gt;fit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best wishes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R%C3%A9sum%C3%A9"&gt;Résumé - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 1 Mar 2019 15:40:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/creating_a_modern__practical_resume</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/creating_a_modern__practical_resume</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Minimalism: A Week of Web Blocking for Productivity and Well-Being</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_week_of_web_blocking_for_productivity_and_well-being/images/addiction_is_life_in_jail.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My productivity has been poor, and a big reason is distraction. Well, that's a nice way to put it, so let's call it what it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a social media and Netflix addict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unsocial-media"&gt;(Un)Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One advised practice in digitial minimalism, and well-being, is to effectively eliminate social media. &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Digital-Minimalism-Choosing-Focused-Noisy-ebook/dp/B07DBRBP7G/ref=sr_1_1"&gt;Cal Newport&lt;/a&gt; suggests rethinking social media in terms of logistics. Facebook isn't social, but it can be a way to schedule actual social (i.e. face-to-face) activies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is social media bad for well-being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;quot;Like&amp;quot; feature is intentionally based on an addictive model to make you check your account. Essentially, you're a rat checking if someone has left you food.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not getting &amp;quot;likes&amp;quot; leads to lower self-esteem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online interaction has far less quality than physical interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale professor &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y6YGZfcAegw&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;list=PLVext98k2eviHGwrB6tNNbvoGB3dUWk0F"&gt;Laurie Santos&lt;/a&gt; recommends her students rid of social media. Newport recommends the same, but allows that there can be value to Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, et. al. if they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used as tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use is severely restricted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="netflicatus-stimulorum"&gt;Netflicatus Stimulorum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as Netflix, Amazon Prime, CW, etc, it's just too easy for me to binge watch. TV and movies can be great for inspiration, and might be critical for people in those fields. But all I think about is how much time I spend on other people's creations instead of creating my own art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="to-the-rescue"&gt;... To the Rescue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've avoided web-blocking apps for years, for the same reason addicts don't go to therapy; they think it shows weakness. But the better way is to think of it in terms of gun ownership. &lt;em&gt;Full disclosure: this example won't sit well with some of you, but the facts are well-documented.&lt;/em&gt; A person with suicidal thoughts is far more likely to successfully kill himself if he owns a gun. Why? Because suicide is mostly an action taken during depression and depends on opportunity. The harder the person has to work at suicide, the less likely he'll take action. Guns are easy and immediate. Poison is harder and takes longer, allowing the person to call for help. Sure, a determined person will find a way. But the studies show that even ten minutes of delay saves lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web-blocking software can work the same way. Sure, I can bypass the software. But I have to &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; do that. If it's a little challenging--maybe I have to look up a password--I probably won't bother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm trying these apps for the next seven days, and I'll report back on my results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/plans"&gt;RescueTime&lt;/a&gt; Free for lite version, which tracks which sites and apps I'm using. Useful for reviewing at the end of the week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mindfulbrowsing.org/"&gt;Mindful Browsing&lt;/a&gt; Free. Nudges a person away from mindless sites with positive pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either &lt;a href="https://www.proginosko.com/leechblock/"&gt;LeechBlock&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stayfocusd/laankejkbhbdhmipfmgcngdelahlfoji?hl=en"&gt;StayFocusd&lt;/a&gt;, extensions to block certain sites on schedules or demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="web-sites-im-blocking"&gt;Web Sites I'm Blocking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Netflix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amazon Video : &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/video"&gt;https://www.amazon.com/gp/video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CW TV and CW Seed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-im-doing-about-facebook"&gt;What I'm Doing About Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the month of February, I committed to only writing positive posts. This has been going well. At the end of February, I'll post about why I'm leaving Facebook, and collect contact information for people I want to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 17:20:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_week_of_web_blocking_for_productivity_and_well-being</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/a_week_of_web_blocking_for_productivity_and_well-being</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revert PackageReference Project to Packages.config</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/revert_packagereference_project_to_packages_config/images/reset.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions below aren't tested in all scenarios, and assume familiarity with Visual Studio, NuGet Package Manager, etc. They should be enough to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backup, branch, or otherwise protect your source first!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To revert from PackageReference to packages.config:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Close the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Delete the project's &lt;code&gt;obj&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bin&lt;/code&gt; folders (which is where the Reference references are stored)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Edit the .csproj file. Remove &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;RestoreProjectStyle&amp;gt;PackageReference&amp;lt;/RestoreProjectStyle&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cut/Paste all PackageReference elements into a separate text editor, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml"&gt;&amp;lt;ItemGroup&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;MSTest.TestAdapter&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Version&amp;gt;1.4.0&amp;lt;/Version&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/PackageReference&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;MSTest.TestFramework&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Version&amp;gt;1.4.0&amp;lt;/Version&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/PackageReference&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;Selenium.WebDriver&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Version&amp;gt;3.141.0&amp;lt;/Version&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/PackageReference&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;Selenium.WebDriver.ChromeDriver&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Version&amp;gt;2.44.0&amp;lt;/Version&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/PackageReference&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ItemGroup&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save and close the .csproj file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open Visual Studio (but not the solution).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Change the VS default package management format to &lt;code&gt;Packages.config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
OR&lt;br /&gt;
Check Allow format selection on first package&lt;br /&gt;
OR&lt;br /&gt;
Add a packages.config file to the project folder with this text:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml"&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot; encoding=&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;packages&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;package id=&amp;quot;MSTest.TestFramework&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1.4.0&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/packages&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: If you don't enable using packages.config, you must manually add at least one of the packages to the xml.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: It's optional, but recommended, to add the targetFramework element with the correct moniker for the project's framework.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you manually created a packages.config file, restore missing NuGet packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If needed, install remaining NuGet packages using package manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build and test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 14:34:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/revert_packagereference_project_to_packages_config</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/revert_packagereference_project_to_packages_config</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Create a Simple Photo Album Site With Wix</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My dad asked for some help creating a photo gallery web page. I suggested a free site on &lt;a href="https://www.wix.com/"&gt;Wix&lt;/a&gt;. Now, Wix is a user-friendly site, but it's really useful to have experience with how content management systems work. My dad's a really good photographer and a terrific musician. He's used computers for a long time. But he's not software guy in the sense that I am. So, he asked for my help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a &amp;quot;here's what to do&amp;quot; guide to creating a simple photography site. It doesn't get into adding new widgets or even pages. Instead, it focuses on &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; several things. Lots of people prefer working this way, because after a few clicks and edits they start to get how the application is intended to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll update this page with a link to his actual site once he's created it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confession&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All the original (non-template) photographs in this post are mine. They're OK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be prepared to spend at least a couple of hours creating a simple site the first time around.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial assumes you've created a Wix account and have ended up on the first of the &amp;quot;getting started&amp;quot; pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So...after this page, you get asked some questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1450.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the way I answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to create a site for &lt;code&gt;myself&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It should be a &lt;code&gt;photography site&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've &lt;code&gt;never done this before.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick a template. I liked this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: It's not possible to change the template afterward. So, either choose one you really like, OR expect that your first site will be a &amp;quot;play around&amp;quot; one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1616.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the video, because it'll be useful later, (the &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; time you watch it), then &amp;quot;Start now&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1646.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the editing page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1647.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &amp;quot;AMANDA WILLMAN&amp;quot; to select the text box. Then, either double-click, or click Edit Text, to change the name. Then, hover over the top border and click/drag the name toward the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1659.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, change and move the smaller text box. In my example, I also selected the text boxes and decreased the box sizes by dragging the handles that appear on the borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1704.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click Save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1707.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll get this prompt. Enter something appropriate like &lt;code&gt;terry-flatt-photography&lt;/code&gt;. Save and Continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not publish, yet. You can change the domain name later, but remember you may decide to completely scrap this site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1705.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click Preview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1710.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see the &amp;quot;A-W&amp;quot; needs to be removed, and also the Store at least needs to be hidden if not removed completely. We also want to change (or remove) the changing photo gallery, and the portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1731.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &amp;quot;Back to Editor. To hide all the controls, click the arrow-tab at the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1735.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now select the A-W text box and press Delete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, click the main photograph. A menu will pop up. Click Change Images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1738.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;quot;Organize Your Gallery Images&amp;quot; tool, you can add, delete and move images, as well as add some descriptions. Let's start really simple. Delete all the existing images. Hover over each image and click the trash can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1740.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now click Add Images and choose a file from your file system. You can click Upload Media, or drag and drop files from a folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Drag and drop didn't work for me, so I clicked Upload Media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1745.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After it's uploaded, an Add Images tool appears. Select the image and click Add to Gallery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1748.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, click Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1749.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That takes care of the first image a visitor will see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1750.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's hide the Store. Click on the Horizontal Menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1755.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Manage Menu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1756.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select Store, click the &amp;quot;triple dot&amp;quot; settings menu, and choose Hide (or Delete). Then close the menu manager by clicking the upper right X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1758.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, select the Cart and delete it by pressing your &amp;lt;Delete&amp;gt; key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1801.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, select the Horizontal Menu and Navigate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1803.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chose &amp;quot;The Desert,&amp;quot; which will open that page. From here, you can change the title and paragraph text as we have before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tip: If the Text Settings tool window gets in the way, click its header and drag it somewhere else on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now click a picture. This will select the Gallery. Click Manage Media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1808.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This opens a tool very much like the one on the home page. You can add, remove and arrange photos. You can also add videos and text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I deleted all the photos, then chose Add Media &amp;gt; Image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1811.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the media tool, you can choose previously uploaded photos, or upload by clicking Upload Media. You can upload multiple images at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1812.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1813.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you can select multiple files to Add to Page by using CTRL/CMD + Click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1816.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the gallery, you can add titles and descriptions. Click Done when finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select the Horizontal Menu &amp;gt; Manage Menu again. Select The Desert's settings, choose Rename, and change the name to Santa Fe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1823.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1824.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the same tool to add, remove and reorder pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves the home page gallery links, and footer, to take care of. Use Horizontal Menu &amp;gt; Navigate to open the Home page again. Then, scroll down to the Desert photo. Select it, Change Image to one in the Santa Fe gallery, then change the text to &amp;quot;Santa Fe.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1829.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scroll down further to the footer. Change the copyright text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1831.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show the Controls. Save the site, view it and then, if desired, publish it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is lot more that can be done with Wix. You might consider creating a &amp;quot;play&amp;quot; site that you don't publish, just to see what you can do with the tools. There's also lots of documentation. Like many photo editing tools, it's &amp;quot;easy once you know how.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I changed the toolbar Design so it was more visible, and moved the name to the header so it appears on every page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix/images/20190103-1842.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy site creating!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 3 Jan 2019 14:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/create_a_simple_photo_album_site_with_wix</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Rules for Successfully Starting a Habit</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/three_rules_for_successfully_starting_a_habit/images/512px-Babisnauer_pappel_morgen.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Wimox" title="User:Wimox"&gt;Henry Mühlpfordt&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"&gt;CC-BY-SA-3.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a summary of the November 6 episode of the Developer Tea podcast, &lt;a href="https://spec.fm/podcasts/developer-tea/223915"&gt;3 Rules for Designing Lasting Habits&lt;/a&gt;. I encourage you to listen to the entire episode, and to subscribe to Jonathon's excellent podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often we conflate the &lt;em&gt;goal&lt;/em&gt; with the &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt;. For example, getting up at 7am each morning isn't a habit. (It seems like one at first, right?) I'll use that goal to illustrate each of the three rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="concept-what-is-a-habit"&gt;Concept: What is a Habit?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A habit is a repeated behavior we do in regular cirumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A habit is part of us, it's normal. &lt;em&gt;It's our default.&lt;/em&gt; For example, whenever I'm about to walk out of the house, or leave a restaurant, I pat my pockets to be sure I have everything:  &lt;em&gt;keys-phone-wallet&lt;/em&gt;. I don't even think about doing it. But if something's missing, I notice. My goal? To not lose those three critical items when I'm in transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="rule-1-focus-on-triggers-not-outcomes"&gt;Rule 1 - Focus on Triggers, Not Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the very earliest, small actions that will start the cascade toward the goal? They don't have to even directly support the goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example habits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set an alarm for 7am. This doesn't guarantee I'll get up, but makes it harder to stay asleep.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Note: since I'd set a repeating alarm, this isn't really a habit. It's a stacking action (see below)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place my phone on my bedside table each night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before going to bed, write down the one thing I'll do at 7am the next morning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First thing after lying in bed and lights out, envision &lt;em&gt;with enthusiasm&lt;/em&gt; the first thing I'll do at 7am the next morning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedule meetings for 8am whenever possible. This makes it unlikely I'll sleep in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more, but this should give you an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="rule-2-slow-pitch-yourself-softballs"&gt;Rule 2 - Slow-Pitch Yourself Softballs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make the first, small habits things you can easily accomplish. Make it easy to hit home runs, both by slow-pitching softballs, and by making the field smaller. Ramp-up instead of going all out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confession&lt;/strong&gt; I've been getting this wrong most of my life. I'd barrel into not just one, but several new goals and habits all at once, succeed for a day or two, then collapse in frustration and shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the first week, have only one meeting at 8am. The next week, two, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For two weeks, pick one day to turn on your alarm for 7am, and keep it off the rest of the days. It could be &amp;quot;Fresh-Start Monday.&amp;quot; Then increase the number of days over remaining weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might seem like &amp;quot;Oh, I got up at 7am one morning, big deal.&amp;quot; But it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a big deal. If you were getting up at 7 zero days before, then getting up early one day is--technically--an infinite improvement! Seriously, reward yourself for your accomplishments, no matter how small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="rule-3-focus-on-compound-and-stacking-returns"&gt;Rule 3 - Focus on Compound and Stacking Returns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose triggering habits that stack with the other habits. These can also be actions. An example from above is setting the alarm. That'sa one-time action, but it stacks on the habit of putting the phone on the beside table. The metaphor is &lt;a href="https://www.thecalculatorsite.com/articles/finance/compound-interest-formula.php"&gt;compounding interest&lt;/a&gt;. What are the early habits and actions that make future habits even more valuable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No computer or screen use starting an hour before bedtime. Research shows this improves sleep quality, which is a key toward waking up when I want to. This benefits every other habit, and carries other benefits for my health as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Gently) stretch when I get up. Notice that this habit isn't time-dependent. But it's a natural and healthier way than coffee to start up the body's blood, oxygen, cortisol, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While all the above are true, for this particular goal it might be valuable to check whether I'm working against my own body. Am I naturally a morning person? Or an evening person? Biology isn't always changeable, and often not easily changeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="encouragement"&gt;Encouragement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to say--or be told--&amp;quot;this needs to be a habit!&amp;quot; But knowing what a habit is, and &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to form a habit, is too often left out of the admonition. The rules above can help you be successful. You can do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Cutrell cites these two books in his podcast:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Power-Habit-What-Life-Business-ebook/dp/B0055PGUYU/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1542148880&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=power+of+habit"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power of Habit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Charles Duhigg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Atomic-Habits-Proven-Build-Break-ebook/dp/B07D23CFGR/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1542148979&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=atomic+habits"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 13:58:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/three_rules_for_successfully_starting_a_habit</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/three_rules_for_successfully_starting_a_habit</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Going Full Screen: When and Why</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why/images/2018-11-07_21-25-35.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Screen Dilemma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One screen&lt;br /&gt;
Two screen&lt;br /&gt;
Full screen&lt;br /&gt;
Lots-o-Windows screen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, I'm no Dr Seuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you're working on an 11&amp;quot; ultraportable, or have three 25&amp;quot; 4K monitors, minute-by-minute you are faced with a decision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I run the current application windowed or full-screen?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may not seem to require much thought. Whatever works, right? But is our decison working for our productivity, or against it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people blow up every application to full-screen and switch back and forth in a mad fit of mouse-clicking. Others keep all their apps on screen and fling them around like Tom Cruise in &lt;em&gt;Minority Report&lt;/em&gt;. I have some opinions on when one or the other is more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat Alert!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don't have science to back up all of these opinions. If you do (or evidence against), send me an email!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contents"&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#principles"&gt;Principles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#windowed-reduced-context-switching"&gt;Windowed: Reduced Context-Switching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#full-screen-reduced-distractions"&gt;Full-Screen: Reduced Distractions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#mixed-mode-just-be-careful"&gt;Mixed Mode: Just Be Careful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#apply-the-same-principle-to-applications"&gt;Apply the Same Principle to Applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#distractions-thoughts-on-wallpaper"&gt;Distractions: Thoughts on Wallpaper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#distractions-thoughts-on-desktop-icons"&gt;Distractions: Thoughts on Desktop Icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#distractions-final-note"&gt;Distractions: Final Note&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#summing-up"&gt;Summing up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="principles"&gt;Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post really rests on two principles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.	Reduce distractions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2.	Reduce task-switching&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are pretty good ideas for lots of things, not just computer use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="windowed-reduced-context-switching"&gt;Windowed: Reduced Context-Switching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better for:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Entry from one source to another&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest leap in productivity and joy for most people is when they move from one screen to two. Even fifteen years ago, Albert Balcells, the vice-president of CoActive Marketing Group's development department, told me, &amp;quot;The studies show that you'll make back the few hundred dollars you spend on a second screen within three weeks.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I commonly hear is, &amp;quot;Wow, now I can have one document open on one screen while I'm working on another!&amp;quot; This is a perfect use case. For example, if I'm researching for a blog post, I'll take notes on one screen while zooming around the web browser in the other. When I'm programming, I have to look up lots of stuff. Keeping the editor in front of me, and a browser full of tabs on a separate screen, triples my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What about three screens?&lt;/em&gt;, you ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use three screens, and find it effective. I'll bet many people do the same thing as I do. One screen is dedicated to just a few apps that are always open and visible. For me it's email, journal and time-boxing timer. I have that monitor oriented in portrait mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why/images/ScreenCap_2018-11-07_21-40-28.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, yeah, if you can afford it, do it. But don't increase your distractions! Apply the same rules to three monitors as you do to one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip: Minimize, Don't Close&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Avoid closing windows when you're temporarily done with them. Learn and anticipate when you'll be going back and forth between applications. If you don't need an application on the screen, minimize it. I've seen lots of users waste lots of time opening Word, opening a document, doing one thing, closing the document, opening another window, then a minute later closing that window and opening Word again. It's exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip: Use Effective Layering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Even with multiple large screens, layering windows on top of one another is inevitable. Do this effectively if you're switching between them. You should always be able to see enough of a window to identify it and open it without completely obscuring some other window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why/images/2018-11-07_21-55-51.gif" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medical Reality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Of course, if you have bad eyes, you'll be going full screen more often. But you can still apply the principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="full-screen-reduced-distractions"&gt;Full-Screen: Reduced Distractions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better for:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heads-down programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long-form reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image/Video editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think we can do creative or cognitively intensive work while listening to music, reading and commenting on social media, checking email, and playing with our phones. We can't. Humans don't multi-task (really, they don't), and are poor at task-switching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lecture Alert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You're not an exception.&lt;/strong&gt; You think you are. I know you do. But you're not. The science on multi-tasking and task-switching is consistent. You shouldn't use the phone in the car either, not even hands-free, because every study for the last twenty-five years shows it doesn't matter, it's just as dangerous as drinking and driving. Stop it. Your life's more important, and so is mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you're writing your grant proposal, or need to get into the programming zone, or focusing on that merchandising layout, go full-screen, minimize any other window that you can, and turn off your distractions. There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; science to back this up, so you don't have to trust me, you can look it up. But save yourself some time and just try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going full-screen not only helps focus on the job at hand, but is also valuable because of the number of tools, toolbars, menus, etc. on high-end applications. For example, if you do photo editing, programming, vector drawing, there could be a &lt;em&gt;hundred or more&lt;/em&gt; things to click in front of you. Multiple windows aren't the only distraction. You might want to reduce what the apps show, too (I touch on this later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="mixed-mode-just-be-careful"&gt;Mixed Mode: Just Be Careful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better for:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-monitor, especially three&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, I work in mixed mode. I have my important windows open and arranged so I can reduce task-switching, and I go full-screen when the need arises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip: Don't Have Actively Moving Windows Open&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In movies, it's really cool to see all these screens with stuff constantly moving on them. But in heads-down mode, it's just another eye-catcher. Just as you can't help watching the TV when you're on a date at a bar, anything else flickering or moving nearby only adds to your distraction. Either minimize it or, in the case of a web browser, switch to a tab that's static.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't tell yourself you can watch &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0830361/?ref_=fn_al_tt_1"&gt;The Lost Room&lt;/a&gt; while coding a banking data integration. You won't fully enjoy the former, and will screw up the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="apply-the-same-principle-to-applications"&gt;Apply the Same Principle to Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a class of applications called &lt;a href="https://balsamiq.com/learn/inspiration/zenware/"&gt;&amp;quot;zenware.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; The idea is that they focus on providing a distraction-free experience. Even if you don't stick with it, try out a few. This may really influence your experience of your everyday apps, and you might find yourself paring down what's on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications' default layouts are often &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the most efficient. They're there to show you the application's capabilities, not improve your work flow. Only keep the tools/frames open that you use frequently. Reduce clutter, but also make it easy to open what you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="distractions-thoughts-on-wallpaper"&gt;Distractions: Thoughts on Wallpaper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a sensitive subject, so definitely take it or leave it. Computer desktop wallpaper is one of the few things users can easily personalize. Except in rare situations, I think businesses should let users set whatever wallpaper they want as long as it's work-appropriate. What that means can be vague, but if there's a question there's an opportunity for better communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I prefer wallpapers that are interesting but also truly fade into the background. My favorites are black-and-white photos that aren't very busy. Try thinking of your computer wallpaper as a canvas, not a photo album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you really want to find out what difference it makes? Switch your wallpaper to plain black, dark grey, or whatever color pleases you (but I wouldn't go super bright). Try that for a week. Then switch back to your other wallpaper. Which is less stressful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a wallpaper I like. It's a photo I took of Winton Woods in Cincinnati, Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why/images/winton-woods-charles-flatt-sm.jpg"&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why/images/winton-woods-charles-flatt-sm.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="distractions-thoughts-on-desktop-icons"&gt;Distractions: Thoughts on Desktop Icons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate them. I especially hate when users have hundreds on their desktop &lt;em&gt;plus&lt;/em&gt; a picture of a puppies playing with ribbons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why/images/ScreenCap_2018-11-07_22-15-20.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the reason so many users use the desktop for storing files and folders is because they've never been taught how to use the Windows Explorer as originally intended. And I don't blame them, because for years Microsoft and Apple have tried to make file management &amp;quot;better&amp;quot; by hiding something everyone can understand if given half a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computer file system is based on physical file cabinets, which have been around for centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big problem with icons on the desktop is that, in order to work with them, you have to minimize open applications. That's a huge time sink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't open applications using desktop shortcuts. Pin them to the task bar, instead, because it's always available. Then delete those shortcuts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On Windows 7 and 10 you can right-click a taskbar app icon to see the most recent files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organize your files in the Documents folder, then keep the Windows Explorer window open or minimized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you must keep icons on the desktop, limit yourself to only the most important you're working on &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;, no more than a dozen, and put them all on the left or right side. Most people seem to prefer the left. This lets you resize windows so that the icons are still in view.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="distractions-final-note"&gt;Distractions: Final Note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep other distractions to an absolute minimum. Do you really need to be notified whenever an email arrives? Does your job require following messaging feeds while trying to focus on the task at hand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most cases, the answer is &amp;quot;no.&amp;quot; Don't let applications interrupt you when they want to. They are not the boss of you. &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; decide when to check email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summing-up"&gt;Summing up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I discovered when writing this post, the real issue isn't whether to run apps full screen or not. It's &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;, and that boils down to distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this will help in some way. I hope it'll inspire you to examine how you're working and try some experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work well!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 7 Nov 2018 18:14:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/going_full_screen-_when_and_why</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NuGet PackageReference in Visual Studio</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/nuget_packagereference_in_visual_studio/images/nuget-vs-logos.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information is accurate as of this writing, as far as I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contents"&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#whats-the-change"&gt;What's the Change?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#what-are-the-advantages"&gt;What Are the Advantages?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#which-visual-studio-editions-and-project-types-does-it-work-with"&gt;Which Visual Studio Editions and Project Types Does It Work With?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#is-there-a-converter"&gt;Is There a Converter?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#manually-converting-to-packagereference"&gt;Manually Converting to PackageReference.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#can-i-convert-with-a-script"&gt;Can I Convert With a Script?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#references"&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-the-change"&gt;What's the Change?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, a project's NuGet package information is stored in a project-level packages.config folder. The assemblies are stored in a separate packages folder, usually at the solution level. The project's .csproj file contains Reference elements that point to the assemblies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Packages.config format folder layout and text samples&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Argonautics
|_packages
  |_ParseText.1.0.4.0
    |_lib
      |_net45
        |_ParseText.dll
        |_PersistText.dll
|_Argonautics.sln
|_PlainPlanning
  |_PlainPlanning.cproj
    &amp;lt;Reference Include=&amp;quot;ParseText.dll, Version=1.0.4.3, Culture=neutral, processorArchitecture=MSIL&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;HintPath&amp;gt;..\packages\ParseText.1.0.4.0\lib\net45\ParseText.dll&amp;lt;/HintPath&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Private&amp;gt;True&amp;lt;/Private&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/Reference&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;Reference Include=&amp;quot;PersistText.dll, Version=2.3.4.0, Culture=neutral, processorArchitecture=MSIL&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;HintPath&amp;gt;..\packages\ParseText.1.0.4.0\lib\net45\PersistText.dll&amp;lt;/HintPath&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Private&amp;gt;True&amp;lt;/Private&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/Reference&amp;gt;
  |_packages.config
    &amp;lt;package id=&amp;quot;ParseText&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1.0.4&amp;quot; targetFramework=&amp;quot;net45&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PackageReference format moves the package information out of packages.config into the .csproj file, and removes the assembly references. The packages folder is removed, as well, in favor of a user-profile folder found at &lt;code&gt;%userprofile%\.nuget\packages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PackageReference format folder layout and text samples&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;Argonautics
|_Argonautics.sln
|_PlainPlanning
  |_PlainPlanning.cproj
    &amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;ParseText&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;Version&amp;gt;1.0.4&amp;lt;/Version&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/PackageReference&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-txt"&gt;|_%userprofile%\.nuget\packages
  |_ParseText.1.0.4.0
    |_lib
      |_net45
        |_ParseText.dll
        |_PersistText.dll
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the project builds, Visual Studio finds the packages in the expected location and copies the assembly dependencies to the bin folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-are-the-advantages"&gt;What Are the Advantages?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Binaries that can be restored are very hard to accidentally include in source control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the package information is shown in References, which is usually what the developer wants to see.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package restore is faster because files aren't copied to a solution folder. Continuous Integration benefits, as well, by having just one well-known package location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Importantly, since the paths to assemblies aren't stored in the .csproj file, version control thrash due to differences between developer environments is eliminated. No more &lt;code&gt;update-package -restore&lt;/code&gt; because DLLs can't be found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PackageReference elemnt allows more flexibity and direct use by MSBuild.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For NuGet Package authors, the nuspec information is stored directly in the project file, not in a .nuspect file. Also, Build and Pack tasks are included in MSBuild.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="which-visual-studio-editions-and-project-types-does-it-work-with"&gt;Which Visual Studio Editions and Project Types Does It Work With?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PackageReference is availabe in Visual Studio 2017. As of this writing, per NuGet.org:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we’re working to bring the PackageReference goodness to all project types and to make all packages compatible with PackageReference, migration is not presently supported for C++, JavaScript, and ASP.NET (.NET Framework) projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, some packages capabilities &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/reference/migrate-packages-config-to-package-reference#package-compatibility-issues"&gt;are not fully compatible&lt;/a&gt; with PackageReference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of scenarios that will not be supported include content folders (we have introduced ContentFiles), XDT transforms, PowerShell scripts i.e. install.ps1 and uninstall.ps1 (only init.ps1 is supported) .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author Note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Obviously ASP.NET support is important, and projects may depend on packages that aren't compatible. However, its lack doesn't prevent migrating compatible projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="is-there-a-converter"&gt;Is There a Converter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is! It's currently available in the &lt;a href="https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/vs/preview/"&gt;Visual Studio Preview&lt;/a&gt; edition. It has some known issues, but seems to work well. See the References for a link to instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="manually-converting-to-packagereference"&gt;Manually Converting to PackageReference.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works with ASP.NET, too, but is more likely to have problems because of content files (stylesheets, scripts, etc). Need to look into this further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backup solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a project's packages.config&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the project's .csproj file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In another text editor, create the PackageReference elements.
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml"&gt;&amp;lt;package id=&amp;quot;Newtonsoft.Json&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;10.0.3&amp;quot; targetFramework=&amp;quot;net461&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml"&gt;&amp;lt;ItemGroup&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;[PackageId]&amp;quot; Version=&amp;quot;[PackageVersion]&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;PackageReference Include=&amp;quot;Newtonsoft.Json&amp;quot; Version=&amp;quot;10.0.3&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ItemGroup&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click References &amp;gt; Manage Nuget Packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose the Installed tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uninstall the packages &lt;em&gt;for the project only&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;There could be more cleanup in .csproj, such as deleting extraneous .target references&lt;/em&gt;*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the ItemGroup into the project file and save.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete packages.config&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Package Manager Console, select the project, and run (for example)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Update-Package -ProjectName Sms.Web.Verifications -Reinstall&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reocmmend doing a file/folder diff from the previous version (easy if using version control). This will reveal problems that a build/run may not catch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="can-i-convert-with-a-script"&gt;Can I Convert With a Script?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't tried a script, yet, but I don't see why not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/consume-packages/package-references-in-project-files"&gt;NuGet PackageReference format (package references in project files) | Microsoft Docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.nuget.org/20180409/migrate-packages-config-to-package-reference.html"&gt;Migrate to PackageReference with 3 clicks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.nuget.org/20170316/NuGet-now-fully-integrated-into-MSBuild.html"&gt;NuGet is now fully integrated into MSBuild&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/what-is-nuget"&gt;What is NuGet and what does it do? | Microsoft Docs&lt;/a&gt; &amp;lt;= This is the top of MS documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dotnetdevaddict.co.za/2017/06/29/evolution-of-the-nuget-packagereference/"&gt;Evolution of the NuGet PackageReference – .NET Development Addict&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.strathweb.com/2018/07/solution-wide-nuget-package-version-handling-with-msbuild-15/"&gt;Solution-wide Nuget package version handling with MsBuild 15+ | StrathWeb. A free flowing web tech monologue.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/msbuild/customize-your-build?view=vs-2017#directorybuildprops-and-directorybuildtargets"&gt;Customize your build - Visual Studio | Microsoft Docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/release-notes/"&gt;Release Notes | Microsoft Docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/NuGet/Home/issues/7241"&gt;Migrate to PackageReference forgets to add PackageReferences! · Issue #7241 · NuGet/Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/NuGet/docs.microsoft.com-nuget/issues/905"&gt;No &amp;quot;Migrate packages.config to PackageReference&amp;quot; · Issue #905 · NuGet/docs.microsoft.com-nuget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image Attributions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By NuGet project team (&lt;a href="https://github.com/NuGet/Media"&gt;https://github.com/NuGet/Media&lt;/a&gt;) [Apache License 2.0 (http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By Microsoft Corporation ([1]) [Public domain], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 13:42:00 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/nuget_packagereference_in_visual_studio</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.softwaremeadows.com/posts/nuget_packagereference_in_visual_studio</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>